<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answer to nine arguments. Written by T. B. Wherein is plainly from the scriptures shewed, the weaknesse of his arguments, whereby he undertakes to prove both the Church and Ministry of England true; as likewise describing the nature and properties of a true Church and Ministry. Written long since by that faithfull servant of God and his countrey, John Lilburne Lieftenant [sic] Collonell: and now published for further good, by a well-willer to him and the truth.</title>
            <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 148 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88157</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2081</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E25_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R212845</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871393</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871393</idno>
            <idno type="VID">154971</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88157)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 154971)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 5:E25[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answer to nine arguments. Written by T. B. Wherein is plainly from the scriptures shewed, the weaknesse of his arguments, whereby he undertakes to prove both the Church and Ministry of England true; as likewise describing the nature and properties of a true Church and Ministry. Written long since by that faithfull servant of God and his countrey, John Lilburne Lieftenant [sic] Collonell: and now published for further good, by a well-willer to him and the truth.</title>
                  <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 43, [1], 1 leaf of plate : port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare of our Lord, 1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With an engraved frontispiece.</note>
                  <note>T. B. is possibly Thomas Bakewell.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Jan: 17th"; the '5' in the imprint has been crossed out; "1644".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bakewell, Thomas, b. 1618 or 19, --  attributed name.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Controversial literature --  Early works 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:154971:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSWER TO NINE ARGUMENTS: Written by <hi>T. B.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WHEREIN IS PLAINLY FROM THE SCRIPTURES ſhewed, the weakeneſſe of his Arguments, whereby he undertakes to prove both the Church and Miniſtery of <hi>England</hi> true; as likewiſe deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing the nature and properties of a true Church and Miniſtery.</p>
            <p>Written long ſince by that faithfull Servant of God and his Countrey, <hi>John Lilburne Leiftenant Collonell:</hi> And now publiſhed for further good, by a well willer to Him and the Truth.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Gal. <hi>4.17.</hi>
               </bibl>
They zealouſly affect you, but not well: they would exclude you, that you might affect them.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1</hi> John <hi>4.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
Beloved beleive not every Spirit, but try the Spirits, whether they be of God, becauſe many falſe Prophets are gon out into the world.</q>
            <p>LONDON.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Yeare of our Lord, 1645.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:154971:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>IOHN LILBURNE. AETAT: SVAE 23. <hi>An<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
                     </hi> 1641.</head>
                  <byline>G: Glo: fecit.</byline>
                  <figDesc>portrait of John Lilburne</figDesc>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Gaze not vpon this shaddow that is vaine,</l>
                     <l>But rather raiſe thy thoughts a higher straine,</l>
                     <l>To GOD (I meane) who ſet this young-man free,</l>
                     <l>And in like straits can eke deliuer thee.</l>
                  </lg>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:154971:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:154971:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154971:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe providence of God bringing to my hands this enſuing Matter, the Author of which thou well knoweſt, if thou beeſt not a <hi>ſtranger in Iſrael,</hi> is famous in Sufferings both for the cauſe of Chriſt in holding him forth to be the only King, and Lawgiver of his Church, againſt that Prelaticall faction which ſtood in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to the ſame, as likewiſe in ſtanding to defend the priviledges of the Kingdom, whereof he is a member, with his liberty, eſtate, and life, as counting nothing dear to himſelfe, that he might render himſelfe faithfull to Chriſt, in giving to him that which was his due, and unblameable to <hi>Caeſar</hi> to give unto him that which is his, reſolving by the ſtrength of Chriſt, that although others that have ſeemed to ſuffer for Chriſt, ſhould deny him, and plead for Baal, yet to ſtand in his integrity, my ſelfe knowing him to be the ſame that he was ſtanding a member of ſuch a Church which he maintaines to be the only ſpouſe of Jeſus Chriſt, I thought good to publiſh to thy vow, that which long ſince was written by him to that end, when he was in the depth of his ſorrowes, or rather ſufferings, cloſe priſoner in Irons in the <hi>Fleet,</hi> is being an Anſwer to ſome, Arguments, which by an Oppoſite to the truth were then written, wherein is unmasked thoſe unſound grounds, by which a falſe church and miniſtery is pleaded for, as likewiſe deſcribing from the Authority of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures the nature and properties both of true church and miniſtery.</p>
            <p>And if it ſhould be Objected by any, that what is here publiſhed, is not uſefull to us, the Prelats being now thrown down, and a Reformation like to be eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed agreable to the Word of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To which Anſwer may be made,</hi> that if it were ſo, ſurely it would put an end to all conteſt of this nature. For what is that Reformation the Word holds out, but only the men ſhould not Lord it over each others conſciences, but to ſerve each other in love, and labour in the uſe of thoſe meanes God hath appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to informe one an other, as knowing it is the worke of the Lord Jeſus alone, as to bring Soules to himſelfe, ſo alſo to enlighten Soules in the knowledge of the truth, as it pleaſeth him, and not men by baniſhments, Chaines, or impriſonments to doe it, as the Prelates have done, and the Presbyters in <hi>Scotland</hi> at this day doe: But ſuch a Reformation except God by a mighty hand interpoſe is like to be no other then a ſcourge to the States, and as contrary to truth in the pure na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb facs="tcp:154971:4"/>
of it as the other, (although it have wore appearance of truth) which will he plainly manifeſted to thoſe whoſe eyes the Lord ſhall open, to helpe to ſee and ez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine what in this enſuing Diſcourſe is ſaid, there be two great evils, which fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently are apt to beare-ſway in the hearts of thoſe that profeſſe Religion which is ſpirituall ſluggiſhnes, which is manifeſted in living vpon other mens light, take<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all for Goſpell which Learned men ſay, without tryall, (<hi>witneſſe</hi> Mr. <hi>Enoch Gray, who hath forſaken the truth to embace this preſent world</hi>) and that great God of the World <hi>ſelfe love,</hi> that <hi>cup of gold in the hand of the whore,</hi> is ſo ſutable to <hi>ſelfe,</hi> that rather then that ſhall be for gon, all the glory of Jeſus Chriſt ſhall be trampled under feet by them: And in my obſerva<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion I have percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved three ſorts of men glued to thoſe evils.</p>
            <p>The firſt is <hi>carnall Profeſſours,</hi> that can content themſelves with a forme of godlines, and therefore <hi>takes all for gould that gliſters,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other two are <hi>Clergie men</hi> and <hi>Lawyers,</hi> who are filled with ſelfe love, that like <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilate</hi> they both joyne together againſt Chriſt and his pure wayes, and what ſhould be the reaſon, that thoſe two ſhould cleave ſo faſt together to goe hand in hand to fight againſt Chriſt, truly I know not, unleſſe they feare that if the truth of Chriſt take place alone, that it will bring ſuch a luſter, with it, as to appeare ſo perſpicuous and cleare upon the faces of all men, as thereby to roote the one out of their Calling, and the other out of their Tythes, and thereby ſpoyle all their glory and greatnes at one blow; and I hope the wiſedome of this preſent Parliament will ſee, that ſuch as that, which now goeth by oppreſſion into their purſes, may be turned to make vp the Kingdomes loſſes, which may with much eaſe be done, if they conſult with God and their neighbour Countrey, <hi>(the Sates of Holland:)</hi> but I ſhall leave that to their wiſedomes, and thee in thee peruſall of this to the bleſſing of the moſt High, and if there be any thing in it that ſavours of harſhnes to thee, let it be looked at by thee as expreſſions of Reſolution rather, knowing that ſuch a ſpirit hath been ſtill manifeſt by him both in the cauſe of God and his Countrey: And therefore I ſhall ſay no more, but reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in all ſervices of love to his power,</hi> M. N.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:154971:4"/>
            <head>AN ANSWEARE TO NINE ARGUMENTS of T. B.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>LOVING FRIEND</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>TO ſatisfie your earneſt deſire to me, I have put pen to paper, to anſweare the ungrounded Arguments of your <hi>Friend,</hi> which you communicated unto me; but to tell you my Judgment of them, in few words: They are of ſuch Inſufficiency, and ſo ungroundedly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piled, without all Authority of holy Scripture; that I doe aſſure you, if it had not been my promiſe to you to reply unto them, I ſhould not once more have ſpent my precious Time and Paines in a ſecond view of them: For in the laying downe of nine Arguments, he hath not one Portion of Gods word to prove them all, but only one; and that is nothing perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent to his purpoſe: but runnes on moſt deceitfully to prove <hi>Logicke</hi> by <hi>Logicke.</hi> Truly, I am affraid he is too neer of kinne to the <hi>Prelate</hi> of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury</hi> and <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Lambeth,</hi> and the reſt of his brother <hi>Biſhops,</hi> that paſſed Cenſure upon that Worthy man Dr. <hi>Baſtwicke</hi> at his Cenſure in the <hi>High-Commiſſion Court,</hi> who there Blaſphemouſly affirmed, that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is the Refuge of all <hi>Heretiques</hi> and <hi>Siſmatiques,</hi> as you may read at large in the Tenth and Eleventh Page of his Anſweare to Sr. <hi>John Bankes</hi> his Information: and <hi>I</hi> beleeve your <hi>Friend</hi> that gave you theſe Arguments thinkes ſo too, or elſe he would have proved that which he had underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; by the Authority of the Sacred Word of God. But <hi>Antichriſts</hi> Owles love and deſire Darkneſſe, and cannot endure to bring their ſayings and actions to the unerring Touch-ſtone of the Holy Scripture, and there to try them, whether they be droſſe or Gold, for <hi>he that doth,</hi> or ſaith <hi>evill hateth</hi>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:154971:5"/>
               <hi>Divells</hi> Inſtitution, and Invention, with which the Limbs of the <hi>Beaſts</hi> Kingdome have for many hundred yeares together, and ſtill doe fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the trueth of God, and the Kingdome and <hi>Scepter</hi> of the Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> And therefore I exhort you, and all thoſe that deſire to feare God and walke in his wais, and love the Salvation of their owne Souls, to take heed of ſuch an Erronious <hi>Sophiſter,</hi> as your ſuppoſed <hi>Freind</hi> is, that gave you theſe Arguments. But becauſe I heare he doth bragge and boaſt, that none of the <hi>Seperation</hi> dare come to particulars, but only run upon generals; therefore to prove him a falſifier of the knowne trueth, and alſo a lyar; I leave my generall ſpeech to you, and come to the unfolding and ripping up every particular in all his Arguments.</p>
            <p>Therefore to my <hi>Oppoſite,</hi> I direct my ſpeech. And in the firſt place you ſay, <hi>You have ſent her (your</hi> Friend) <hi>thoſe Arguments which doe prove your</hi> Mother <hi>the</hi> Church <hi>of</hi> England <hi>to be a true</hi> Mother.</p>
            <p>To which I anſwear, ſhe is a true <hi>Whoriſh Mother,</hi> and you are one of her <hi>Baſe-begotten</hi> and <hi>Baſtardly Children,</hi> for you know a <hi>Whore</hi> is a woman as truly as a true wife, and ſhe may have Children as proportionable as the Children of a true wife; yet this doth not prove her Children which are <hi>Baſe-begotten</hi> are <hi>true-begotten</hi> Children becauſe they have all the parts and Limbs of Children that are begotten in a true married Eſtate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition: even ſo ſay I, the Church of <hi>England,</hi> neither is, nor never was truly married; joyned, or united to <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> in that Eſpouſall bond which his true Churches are and ought to be: but is one of <hi>Antichriſts</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall, <hi>Whoriſh</hi> Churches, or Cities ſpoken of <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.19. united, joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, knit to the <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Lambeth,</hi> as Head and Husband thereof; being ſubſtitute to the <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> from whom he hath received his <hi>Arch-Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopall</hi> Power, and Authority, as you may read in the beginning of <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wins</hi> Catalogue of <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and in the laſt Page of <hi>Francis Maſons</hi> Epiſtle Dedicatory to <hi>George Abbot: William Lauds</hi> Prediceſſour, in his booke of <hi>Biſhops, Prieſts, Deacons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, you confeſſe the Church of <hi>England</hi> is a Scratched and Defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Mother, in ſome reſpects which you could wiſh were reformed, and removed from her. To which I reply, ſhe is a <hi>Whoriſh</hi> Mother, and that is Deformity inough; for though a <hi>Whore</hi> be never ſo perſonable, and Compleat a Woman in all outward reſpects, yet if ſhe be a <hi>Whore,</hi> there is Deformity inough in that alone, to ſpoyle all her perſonall Comlineſſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:154971:5"/>
and parts. But it is much you will confeſſe your Mother is Scratched and deformed in ſome reſpects, ſeing in your enſuing Arguments you ſay, you have the true matter of a Church, and true Forme, true Salvation, true Religion, and true Worſhip: but if you have all theſe, it is a wonder to me, wherein her Deformity can be; therefore I pray you the next time no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate, and particular your Mothers Deformities, that I may know them by your owne confeſſion. But put the caſe I ſhould deny (as juſtly I may) that you have neither true matter, true Forme of a viſible Church, nor true Religion, nor true Worſhip: I doubt I ſhould ſo perplex you to prove it, that all your <hi>Sophiſticall, decievable, Logiſticall, Philoſophicall</hi> Arguments would be to ſcant to make it good: but I let it alone in this place, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre it to the enſuing diſcourſe, where it will come in more pertinent.</p>
            <p>But if you could wiſh your Mothers Deformities were removed, then, why doe you not tell her of them? and labour to diſcover them unto her, that ſo her Deformed Face may be made ſtrait and Comly? truly in my judgement you are but a very unnaturall and unloving ſonne, that ſees your Mothers Deformities, and wiſhes they were removed from her, and yet will not ſtrive to your utmoſt (as is your duty) to purge her from them that ſhe may be, inſtead of a deformed Mother, a wholl and beutiful Mother.</p>
            <p>Againe, in the Third place you ſay, <hi>That your Labour may be effectuall to your</hi> Friend, <hi>you would have her to obſerve theſe five things.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1 <hi>Rightly to apprehend the trueth of your Arguments.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 <hi>To hold her thoughts largely upon them.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3 <hi>To ſtrive to beleeve them.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4 <hi>That ſhe ſhould ſtrive to remember the danger that will follow the neglect of them.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5 <hi>That ſhe ſhould goe to</hi> God <hi>by</hi> Prayer <hi>to make them effectuall to her, for her good.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>For the anſwearing of which, in the firſt place, <hi>You would have her right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to apprehend the trueth of your Arguments.</hi> But how can ſhe apprehend trueth in thoſe Arguments that have nothing but falſity in them, as by Gods aſſiſtance I ſhall make it appeare in my enſuing diſcource, and if ſhe ſhould apprehend the trueth of them indeed, ſhe may juſtly ſay thus much of them, that they are all <hi>Sophiſtry</hi> and ungrounded Arguments, being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of any Authority from the holy Scriptures.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:154971:6"/>2. In the Second place, <hi>You would have her hold her thoughts largly upon them.</hi> Truly if ſhe ſhould doe ſo, ſhe ſhould exceedingly wrong her owne Soull, for will you have her put Confidence in the broken <hi>Reeds</hi> of <hi>Egipt?</hi> which will pierce and runne into her hand when ſhe moſt truſts to them? but ſuch are all your Arguments, being no better then Bulruſhes which the Two-edged Sword of Gods Word, at one blow will cut them all in pieces: and if ſhe have no better Weapons to defend her felfe with, then theſe, ſhe may come to beundon by them, by being more ſtrenghtened &amp; confirmed in Errour and ſo lie open and liable unto Gods heavy <hi>Judgments, Plagues</hi> and <hi>Vengence,</hi> which he hath threatned to pour downe in aboundance upon all thoſe that worſhip the <hi>Beaſt. Rev.</hi> 14.9.10. and this is the <hi>Beaſt</hi> that ſhe ſhall get by keeping her thoughts largely upon them: and therefore her ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt courſe is to compare them with the infallible Word of God, by which ſhe ſhall ſee it is her duty to keepe her thoughts upon them as litle as ſhe can, leaſt ſhe pay too deere for her ſo doing <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.20.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In the third place, <hi>You would have her to beleeve them.</hi> I pray tell me whether you have the Spirit of God infallibly? that you cannot erre in that which you ſay: that you would have her ſo confidently to beleive your Arguments, without any proofe unto them from the Authority of the Word of God, which is the only binder of the Conſcience. Indeed ſhe hath but a blind Guide of you, &amp; an ignorant Leader, &amp; if ſhe follow your guiding &amp; leading, you will lead her into more <hi>Rebellion</hi> againſt <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> his <hi>Scepter</hi> and <hi>Kingdome;</hi> and ſo bring miſery inough upon her, for Chriſt hath threatned to ſlay all thoſe his enemies, which will not have him to rule over them, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.21. and if he dyed without mercy under two or three witneſſes, that rejected <hi>Moſes</hi> Law, of how much ſorer puniſhment thinke you ſhall they be worthy of, that reject the commandements of Jeſus Chriſt? as both ſhee and you do for the preſent: therefore, let her looke to it, and take heed of giving to much credit to your <hi>Hereticall</hi> and <hi>Erronious</hi> ſayings, for are the things that you ſay of more authority then the ſayings of Chriſt himſelfe, or his Apoſtles, or the Angells of heaven, that ſhe muſt believe them before by the divine Scripture you have proved them? truly you take more Authority upon you then Chriſt would doe, for he would not have the <hi>Jews</hi> to beleeve him upon his bare ſayings, but the <hi>Scripture</hi> that did beare witnes of him <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.17.18. <hi>It is written in your Law</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that the Teſtimony of two men is true, non</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>I am one that beare witneſſe of my ſelfe, and my Father
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:154971:6"/>
that ſent me beares witneſſe of me.</hi> So that you ſee Chriſt would not have the <hi>Jews</hi> to beleeve him upon his bare ſayings only, but he brings his <hi>Father</hi> and the holy <hi>Scripture</hi> to beare witneſſe what he is, and then commands them to beleeve him. Alſo <hi>Paull</hi> would not have the <hi>Galathians</hi> to beleeve either him or an <hi>Angell</hi> from Heaven, but to hold them accurſed if they bring any thing contrary to the <hi>Scripture Chap</hi> 1.19. but you would have your <hi>Friend</hi> to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve your Arguments, and yet doth not bring two Portions of <hi>Scripture</hi> to prove them all: therefore I againe adviſe her neither to beleeve you nor your ſayings, becauſe there is no light of trueth in you, ſeing that you goe not to the <hi>Law</hi> and the <hi>Teſtimony</hi> to prove that you ſay, as you ought and ſhould do, <hi>Eſay.</hi> 8.20. therefore ſhe is bound to reject your Arguments, as <hi>Vngrounded, Antichriſtian,</hi> and <hi>Erronious,</hi> and to <hi>Search the Scripture her ſelfe, for that is it that truly teſtifies of</hi> Chriſt, <hi>and of his waies. Joh.</hi> 5.39.</p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>You would have her to remember the danger that will follow upon the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of them.</hi> Your ſaying were very good if it were grounded upon the word of God but ſeing (as I have already, and will more fully make it appeare) they are not, I would have her remember the danger that will follow the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of them, which will be very great, and terrible, for the things that you would have her to give Eare unto, will teach her to rebell againſt the voyce of God himſelfe, who hath commanded all his faithfull people and ſervants, to give Eare to Chriſt only, and alone, in all things that pertaine to life and Salvation, and his Worſhip and Service. <hi>Act.</hi> 3.22.23. <hi>For Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes truly ſaid unto the</hi> Fathers, <hi>a</hi> Prophet <hi>ſhall the</hi> Lord <hi>your</hi> God <hi>raiſe up unto you of your Brethren, like unto me, him ſhall yee hear in all things whatſoever he ſhall ſay unto you: and it ſhall come to paſſe, that every</hi> Soull <hi>that will not heare that</hi> Prophet, <hi>ſhall be deſtroyed from among the People.</hi> So you ſee what Doome the <hi>Scripture</hi> ſaith will befall all thoſe that will not give Eare, nor ſtoope unto all the Lawes of Chriſt, as well for the governing of his Church, as the <hi>Salvation</hi> of their <hi>Soules:</hi> for <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> hath been as faithfull yea more faithfull in his Houſe, then <hi>Moſes</hi> was in his, under the Law. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 3. who was ſtrictly tied to make all things according to the patterne ſhewed him in the Mount: yea, even to the very Pinnes of the Tabernacle. <hi>Exod.</hi> 25.9.40. and 26.30. and 27.9. Which <hi>Moſes</hi> cauſed accordingly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly to be made, and accompliſhed. <hi>Ex.</hi> 30.43. &amp; this <hi>Moſes</hi> did but as a ſervant but Jeſus Chriſt was faithfull in all things that pertains to the wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of his
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:154971:7"/>
Churrch under the Goſpell, as a ſonne: and none may adde or defract from that which he hath done, and left in his laſt Will and Teſtament: but now if ſhe ſhould give Fare to your Grounds, ſhe ſhould declare and ſay in her actions, that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> hath not been ſo faithfull in his houſe, or Church, as <hi>Moſes</hi> was in his; which were to tell the Spirit of God he lyes, therefore let her looke to the danger that will follow her keeping thoſe things which you would have her to obſerve.</p>
            <p n="5">5 In the fift and laſt place, <hi>You would have her to goe to</hi> God <hi>by</hi> Prayer <hi>to make them Effectuall to her, for her good:</hi> but if ſhe ſhould doe ſo, ſhe ſhould put up an unacceptable and ſinfull prayer, for the prayer that any puts up to him for the keeping and confirming them in their Errours, is deteſtable and Odious to him; but thoſe things that you would have her to goe to God for, that they might be Effectuall for her good; are groſſe Errours, and therefore I affirme it is her ſin, if either ſhe pray to be kept in them, or doe not forthwith reject them.</p>
            <p>Well, but now to come to grapple with your ſtrong Arguments, and the firſt of them is thus framed.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>1</label>
               <hi>That</hi> People <hi>or</hi> Nation <hi>that is dayly within the voyce and call of</hi> God, <hi>cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them to Repentance, that ſo they may be ſaved, that ſame is a true viſible</hi> Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But the People (generally) of</hi> England <hi>are within the voyce of</hi> God, <hi>calling upon them to repent, and beleeve; that ſo they may be ſaved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore the</hi> Church <hi>of</hi> England <hi>is a true viſible</hi> Church.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> This is the Frontiſpiece of your worke, and in the laying of it downe you declare, that you doe not in the leaſt underſtand what the matter of a true Church is, which is to conſiſt of beleevers <hi>Acts.</hi> 2.41.47. and not of people uncalled to God, and the knowledge of his trueth <hi>Act.</hi> 2.30.5.13. And this I will (by the ſtrenght of God) fully prove by and by, and therefore if the reſt of your Arguments be no ſtronger then this, they will prove no ſtronger to bind your oppoſers, then the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> flaxen Cords were to bind <hi>Sampſon,</hi> who when he had a mind to be looſed from them, they became as flax burnt with fire: and juſt ſuch are your Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, no more able to hold off and keepe backe the trueth from being ſet at Liberty, then <hi>Dellilahs</hi> greene Withes with which ſhe tyed <hi>Sampſon</hi> were able to keepe him bound that his Enemies might ceaſe uppon him; for he broke them as a Threed of Tow is broken when it toucheth the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:154971:7"/>
               <hi>fire, Judg.</hi> 16. 9. But now to the matter. I abſolutely deny your Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>And firſt for your <hi>Major.</hi> I cannot but expreſſe my Sorrow for you, to ſee you, who are ſo mighty a <hi>Champian</hi> as you boaſt your ſelfe to be, to reaſon ſo ſhallowly and ungroundedly, for if your Argument be true, then all the Nations under <hi>Heaven</hi> are true viſible Churches of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> for it is not poſſible that the <hi>Heatheneſt</hi> Nation in the <hi>World</hi> ſhould runne out of <hi>Gods</hi> Voyce and Call. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.7.8.9. <hi>For</hi> (ſaith Dauid) <hi>If I aſcend up into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven thou art there if I make my Bed in Hell behold thou art there, if I take the Wings of the Morning, and dwell in the uttermoſt part of the Sea, even there ſhall thy hand lead me, and thy right hand ſhall hold me, if I ſay ſurely the dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knes ſhall cover me, even the night ſhall be light about me, yea, the darknes hideth not from thee, but the night ſhineth as the day, the darknes and the light are both alike to thee.</hi> And alſo ſee <hi>Amos.</hi> 9.1.2.3. Where you may alſo read that no place can hide a people from Gods preſence or call; ſo that I ſay no place can exempt a people from Gods voyce, but whereſoever they are he can find them out, and by his <hi>Judgements</hi> laid upon a <hi>Nation</hi> or <hi>Peeple,</hi> whether they be <hi>Pagans, Heathens</hi> and <hi>Infidels</hi> that profeſſedly ſerve and worſhip <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols,</hi> and nothing elſe: or whether they be a <hi>Nation</hi> of ſeeming <hi>Chriſtians</hi> (as <hi>England</hi> is no more) like the <hi>Samaritanes</hi> that profeſſe the <hi>Worſhip</hi> of the true <hi>God,</hi> and yet ſerve their <hi>Idols.</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> 17.32.33. yet take them in which ſence you will, <hi>I</hi> ſay they are within the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>oyce</hi> and call of <hi>God,</hi> and by his <hi>Judgements</hi> and <hi>Plagues</hi> laid upon them for their ſinnes, he calls them to <hi>Repentance</hi> that ſo they might not periſh, but be ſaved: as the Apoſtle <hi>Paull</hi> in the firſt of the <hi>Romans</hi> doth largly prove. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ.</hi> 18.19, and ſo forward. So that by your Argment, all the <hi>Nations</hi> under <hi>Heaven</hi> are <hi>viſible Churches</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> for I thus frame my Argument according to your owne grounds.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All the Nations of the Earth that are within the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>oyce and call of</hi> God, <hi>cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them to Faith and Repentance that ſo they may be ſaved are true</hi> Churches.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But all the</hi> Pagan <hi>and</hi> Heathen <hi>Notions in the World are within the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>oyce and call of</hi> God, <hi>as I have already proved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ergo. <hi>They are true viſible</hi> Churches.</p>
            <p>Deny any part of the Argument if you can, and prove againſt it.</p>
            <p>But for the proofe of your Argument you cite. <hi>Math.</hi> 20.16. where it is ſaid, <hi>Many are called, but few choſen.</hi> the firſt part of the words, <hi>Many are called,</hi> (you ſay but doe not prove) that we are to underſtand them of the viſible Church, which are called to the outward preaching of the word: to which I anſwere, and ſay, you are not an Oracle of God that we muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve your ſayings without ground, for you bring no proofe for what you ſay, but your owne bare Affirmations, but if you will be an Oraclo, it is but a lying Oracle, and not of Gods: you ſay they are called to the outward
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:154971:8"/>
preaching of the Word, it ſeemes to me that you will have all the people in a Nation, that are within Gods call to be Preachers (and then what ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of all your Preiſts? for if this be not your meaning, I know not what you drive at, but for that place of Scripture <hi>many are called, but few are choſen,</hi> I underſtand it thus, many there was that heard the Word of God, and ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, profeſſed it, as they that came to <hi>Johns Baptiſme,</hi> and <hi>Herod</hi> that refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med many things, and thoſe many great multitudes that Chriſt preached un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, many of which made an outward profeſſion of him for a time, but it was but for the loaves, as he himſelfe doth witneſſe, <hi>John</hi> 6.26.27. ſo here are many called to the outward profeſſion of, the Goſpell, but ſaith the Text <hi>few are choſen,</hi> that is to ſay, ehough there be many that make a formall profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſt, and have the ouiſide of Chriſtianity, <hi>yet few are they that are choſen,</hi> either to Chriſts glorious kingdome with his father, or are choſen and admitted as viſible members and Subjects in his viſible Church, or King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, which in Scripture hath many and divers names, as, <hi>Syon, Jeruſalem, his holy Mountaine, the Lords holy place, the kingdome of Heaven, Pſal.</hi> 54.7.147.12. <hi>Fſa</hi> 62.6.65.9.11. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.17.33.46.4. <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.1. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.1.10. this expoſition of the place I plainly prove from Chriſts preaching to ſo many as he did, the moſt of which for a time did outwardly proſeſſe him, yet all thoſe great multitudes that he preached unto, and wrought Miracles amongſt at his death there was but an hundred and twenty that entered into commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion to worſhip him in a viſible Church, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.15. and in the ſecond of the <hi>Acts Peter</hi> preached to a great multitude of people yet that multitude were not members of a true viſible Church, neither before he preached to them, nor after, but only ſo many of them as declared and manifeſted faith which were to the Number of three Thowſand, and they were added or joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the Church, and the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> commands them to ſave or ſeperate themſelves from the reſt of the multitude which he preached unto, ſeing they did not peleeve, nor were never the better for his preaching: ſaying, <hi>Save your ſelves from thes untoward Generatron. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ.</hi> 40.41. For the Lord would not have them to joyne <hi>Riffe Raffe</hi> and all ſorts of people to the Church, to whom the Word was preached, but only thoſe that declared the worke of Grace to be wrought in their hearts, therefore the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>God</hi> ſaith <hi>The</hi> Lord <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the</hi> Church <hi>daily, ſuch as ſhould be ſaved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now though I grant the <hi>Kingdome</hi> of <hi>England</hi> is within the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>oyce</hi> and call of God, calling the people thereof to Repentance, that ſo they may be ſaved, yet I grant no more then what all the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons under Heaven are, therefore you cannot conclude from this Ground that the Church of <hi>England</hi> is a true Church of <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſeing the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:154971:8"/>
Whol <hi>Nation,</hi> good or bad, wicked or righteous, godly or ungodly, have all one and the ſame <hi>Priviledge,</hi> by virtue of their being profeſſed <hi>Membees</hi> of your Ch. &amp; therefore from that which hath been ſaid, I frame this Argument.</p>
            <p>That the true viſible Church of <hi>Chriſt</hi> under the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> doeth not conſiſt of all ſorts and kinds of people to whom the word of God is preached, but only to ſuch perſons, who by their outward Converſation may be judged to be true Beleevers. <hi>Eſay.</hi> 4.3.35.8.9.10.51.11. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.7. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.14.</p>
            <p>But the Church of <hi>England</hi> is not made up, nor doeth not conſiſt of true Beleevers, that is to ſay Saints by calling and practice, but of all ſorts and kinds of wicked perſons, as <hi>Witches, Sorcerers, Whoremungers, Drunkards I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolaters, Swearers, Blaſphemers</hi> &amp; all ſorts of <hi>Prophane, Lewd</hi> &amp; <hi>Wicked</hi> livers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ergo,</hi> It is no true Church of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but a falſe and <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> Church of <hi>Antichriſts,</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9.10. <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.20.21. <hi>and</hi> 13.8.16.17. <hi>and</hi> 21.27. <hi>and</hi> 22.15.</p>
            <p>Both the Propoſition and Aſſumption, I have already ſtrongly proved by the Authority of the <hi>Scripture.</hi> and deny either of them, and prove againſt them, if you be able.</p>
            <p>Againe, your ſecond Argument to prove the Church of <hi>England</hi> a true Church is this. <hi>That Miniſtry which doeth accompliſh the ſame and which the Miniſtry of the Apoſtles did, muſt needs be a true Miniſtry. But the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of the Church of</hi> England <hi>doeth accompliſh the ſame ends that the Apoſtles Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry did, namely converſion and confirmation. Therefore the Miniſtry of the Church of</hi> England <hi>muſt needes be true.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to prove your Argument, you bring not one Place of Scripture but take that for granted which I confidently thinke neither you nor none in the Ch. of <hi>Engl.</hi> are ever able to prove, therefore I abſolutely &amp; in every reſpect deny your Arg. &amp; two manner of waies prove againſt it. 1. I will prove that if the <hi>Miniſtry</hi> in the Ch. of <hi>Engl.</hi> did accompliſh the ſame ends that the <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> did, yet for all that, that is not ſufficient to prove it a true <hi>Miniſtry;</hi> for to judge the cauſe by the effect is a <hi>Leaden</hi> and falſe Rule. 2. I will prove that the <hi>Miniſtry</hi> in <hi>Engl.</hi> doth not accompliſh the ſame ends that the <hi>Miniſtry</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtls</hi> did, &amp; therfore by your own Arg. is no true <hi>Miniſtry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now for the firſt of theſe which anſwers the <hi>Major</hi> of your Arg. I ſay it hath beene and ſtill may be poſſible, for a man to accompliſh the ſame ends that you here ſpeake of, namely to be an Inſtrument to bring Gods people to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation of <hi>Faith,</hi> &amp; alſo to build them up, &amp; yet be no true <hi>Officer</hi> or <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> in the Ch. of <hi>God,</hi> &amp; I prove it out of the <hi>Acts</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> in which we read <hi>that when the</hi> Ch. <hi>began to encreaſe,</hi> Saul <hi>raiſed a great perſecution againſt it upon which, all the brethren viz. the members of the</hi> Ch. <hi>were ſcattered abroad, &amp; they went up &amp; down preaching the word Act</hi> 8.3. <hi>but the Apoſtles themſelves
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:154971:9"/>
they ſtayed ſtill at Jeruſalem. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ.</hi> 1. Now all thoſe that were ſcatterd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad were not true <hi>Officiall Miniſters,</hi> for they were but <hi>Lay-men</hi> according to your diſtinction in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> yet divers of them who were no true <hi>Officers,</hi> but <hi>Bretheren, Diſciples,</hi> or <hi>private men</hi> as you call them, yet they preached the <hi>Word</hi> to the <hi>Gentiles</hi> there &amp; begot by their preaching ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>any of them to the <hi>Faith,</hi> for the <hi>Text</hi> ſaith. <hi>The hand of the Lord was with them, and a great number of them beleeved, and then came</hi> Barnabas <hi>from</hi> Jeauſalem, who was yet no true <hi>Officer</hi> in the Church <hi>of</hi> God, <hi>being as yet uncalled to his</hi> Apoſtleſhip, <hi>and he confirmed and ſtrengthened, and more fully built them up in the</hi> Faith <hi>of</hi> Chriſt <hi>and in the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the wayes of</hi> God. <hi>Alſo</hi> Aquilah, <hi>and his wife</hi> Priſcilla <hi>did further in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct and build up that Eloquent man</hi> Apollos. <hi>Act.</hi> 18.26. <hi>Alſo there were certaine women that laboured with</hi> Paull <hi>in the</hi> Goſpell. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.3.</p>
            <p>So that here you ſee, and I have proved it, that people may be called to the manifeſttaion of Eaith, and further built up by thoſe that are no true <hi>Officers</hi> or <hi>Miniſters</hi> in the Church of <hi>Chirſt:</hi> but if your Argument were true then it would follow that all thoſe men, yea and the women too were true <hi>Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers</hi> and <hi>Miniſters</hi> in the Church of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> becauſe they were Inſtruments of bringing Gods people to the manifeſtation of <hi>Faith,</hi> and further built them up, but your Argument is rotten and unſound, and falls here flat to the ground, and therefore if I ſhould grant it (which I doe not) that your <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> by their <hi>Miniſtry</hi> did accompliſh the ſame ends, that the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> by their <hi>Miniſtry</hi> did, yet this would not be ſufficient to prove them true <hi>Officers</hi> or <hi>Miniſters,</hi> for the excecution of an <hi>Office</hi> doeth not prove an <hi>Officer</hi> but only a true and lawfull call into the <hi>Office,</hi> which all your <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Minni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> in <hi>England</hi> want, and therefore are no true <hi>Officers,</hi> nor no true <hi>Miniſters</hi> of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> For you know that a <hi>King</hi> hath many in his Kingdome beſides himſelfe, that doe thoſe actions &amp; adminiſter thoſe adminiſtrations that is peculiar to him alone to doe and adminiſter, unleſſe they were Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized by virtue of a power given and derived from him to do ſuch actions without a lawfull Authority given and received from him, they might looſe their lives for the doing of them: but now if your Argument were true, that all thoſe men that are meanes, or Inſtrumenſts to bring Gods People to the manifeſtation of Faith, and obedience to the Law and will of Chriſt, were true Officers and Miniſters of Chriſt, it would follow by the ſame Argument, that all thoſe men that doe the actions of a King, or accompliſh the ſame ends, that Kings by their actions doe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh, are true Kings but ſo to conclude in England is little better then High Treaſon: Therefore your Argument is erroneous,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:154971:9"/>
and falſe, and hath not validity in it: for if ſo be you will have their Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrations to prove the lawfulneſſe of their Office, then I pray you, wherein doth the execution of their Office conſiſt? for an Office and the execution of it are two diſtinct things: for a man by virtue of being inſtated into the Office of a Judge though he never live to execute any of thoſe acttions, or Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrations that belong to his place, or Office: but he muſt firſt receive power to ſit in Court of Judicature, before he dare take upon to fit there as Judge; and when he hath receiced power from the King by virtue of which he is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtated into his Office, and doth become an Officer, then doth he lawfully ſit in Court of Judicature, and condemneth fellons and guilty perſons, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit the innocent, and doth there paſſe ſentence according to the Lawes, for the King under whom he is a Judge: But now if this Judge ſhould uſurpe his place, and come into it by virtue of a falſe Authority, and then condemne the Kings Subjects to death, though they be theives and malefactors, yet he would be in danger of looſing his life for all that, though he doe the act and actions that belong to a true Judge to doe, becauſe he had no lawfull Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity from the King ſo to doe: for it is the Kings Authority placed upon a man, that doth make that perſon, to be an other kind of perſon then before he was; for before he had received this power he was but a private man, but now he is an other kind of man; namely, a a publike perſon, in Office, and Authority, and may lawfully do thoſe actions now, which if he ſhould have done before would have coſt him his life: Even ſo is it with the Miniſters and Officers which Jeſus Chriſt hath inſtituted in his New Teſtament, and left perſonally to officiate in his Church; they muſt be members of an incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porated or conſtituted City, body, or viſible Church, and then if the Church find any amongſt themſelves fitted, or qualified according to thoſe guifts, and qualifications which the Apoſtle layes downe in the firſt of <hi>Timothy</hi> the 3. &amp; 5. chapters, and the firſt or <hi>Titus:</hi> then the Church hath authority to chuſe them for her Officers, <hi>Num.</hi> 8.9.10. <hi>Ezeck.</hi> 33.2. <hi>Acts</hi> 1.23.6.3.5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 14.24. but though they be never ſo fitted, guifted, and qualified, yet they are not to take upon them to officiate in the Church of God, by virtue of an Office, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they have a true and lawfull Call from the Church, who only and alone hath power from Chriſt, her only King and Head to inſtate them into that Office, and whereas before they were but members or private men, (as you in the Church of <hi>England</hi> call them) and could not lawfully doe thoſe actions that belong to a true Miniſter, or Officer in the Church of God to doe, yet now they may doe them upon grounded grounds, for it is only their lawfull Call, into their Office that puts a diſtinction betwixt them, and the other members, or Brethren of the Church, as is plaine out of the firſt of the <hi>Acts,</hi> where <hi>Joſeph</hi> and <hi>Matthias</hi> were by the Apoſtles and Brethren ſet a part for the Apoſtleſhip, and <hi>Joſeph</hi> for any thing I know was as well fitted for the Office as <hi>Matthias</hi> was, for the Church was not able to put a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:154971:10"/>
them, which was the more fit, but yet for all this they were not both <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> but only <hi>Matthias</hi> who was lawfully choſen, and immediatly called by <hi>God</hi> into the <hi>Office,</hi> and then thoſe actions that he did and <hi>Adminſtrations</hi> that he adminiſtred, was the execution of his <hi>Office,</hi> ſo that it any ſhould have queſtioned him whether he was an <hi>Apoſtle</hi> or no, he would not runne to the <hi>Adminiſtration</hi> or <hi>Execution</hi> of his <hi>Office</hi> to prove himſelfe <hi>a</hi> true <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> but he would goe to his Call into his <hi>Office</hi> which was from God, and which gave him a being in his <hi>Office,</hi> and power to <hi>Officiate</hi> and doe thoſe actions that he did: and though he had nev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> lived to have executed any of thoſe actions that belonged to his <hi>Office,</hi> yet he had been a true <hi>Apoſtle</hi> for all thae; by vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of his Call into his <hi>Apoſtleſhip.</hi> So that I ſay to you of your <hi>Miniſters,</hi> it is not ſufficient for them when they tre queſtioned about their Calling, and put upon it to prove it, whether it be from God or the Diuell (the one of which it muſt needs be) to runne to the <hi>Execution</hi> and <hi>Adminiſtration</hi> of their <hi>Office,</hi> to prove the lawfullneſſe of their ſtandings in their <hi>Office;</hi> but they ſhould goe to the power and Authority that inſtituted them into their <hi>Office</hi> of <hi>Prieſthood,</hi> and prove it whether it be true or no, which if they cannot doe: I ſay they are all falſe and <hi>Antichriſtain Officers</hi> and <hi>Miniſters,</hi> which all <hi>Gods</hi> people are bound in <hi>Conſcience</hi> to deteſt as the <hi>Divell,</hi> and oppoſe to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of their power, and ſtrength, and therefore I put you upon it to prove (if you can) the lawfulnes of their ſtanding, for doe you thinke that they which are <hi>Antichriſts Miniſters</hi> have a greater priveledge of exempion from proving the lawfulnes of their <hi>Calling</hi> and <hi>Office,</hi> when they are queſtioned, then either that great <hi>Prophet Jihn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> or <hi>Joſus Chriſt</hi> the ſonne of <hi>God,</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> had? truly I ſee no <hi>Ground</hi> nor <hi>Reaſon</hi> for it, unleſſe you will ſay their bare word is of greater <hi>Authority</hi> then the words of the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall Sonne</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For firſt of all, <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> when he was queſtioned by the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> what he was, he doeth not ſay <hi>It is ſufficient that I doe the worke of a</hi> Prophet, <hi>and therefore you need not nor have noe ground to queſtion me any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther about my Authority:</hi> no he knew ſuch an Anſwer would not ſerve their turne, and therefore when they aske him what he was, he <hi>confeſſed that he was not the</hi> Chriſt, <hi>what then art thou? ſay they to him: art thou</hi> Elias? <hi>and he ſaith I am not, who then art thou? he ſaid I am the voyce of one caying in the</hi> Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe <hi>make ſtraight the way of the</hi> Lord <hi>as ſaith the Prophet</hi> Eſay as <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.19.20. and ſo forward.</p>
            <p>So you ſee <hi>John</hi> brings Authority from the Scripture to prove his <hi>Office,</hi> &amp; doeth not runne as your Prieſts doe to the Adminiſtration or Execution of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:154971:10"/>
his Office, to prove his Office, or the lawfulneſſe of his ſtanding in it. Alſo Chriſt himſelfe when he was queſtioned by the <hi>Jewes</hi> about his <hi>miracles,</hi> and thoſe <hi>great workes which he wrought,</hi> by virtue of what authority he did them, he anſwers, and ſaith, <hi>If I beare witneſſe of my ſelfe, my witneſſe is not true,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he brings his Father, and <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> and the <hi>holy Scripture</hi> to beare witnes of him, that he did not take up his authority that he exerciſed of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, neither did he come unto them of his owne head and in his owne name, but brings the <hi>voyce</hi> of his <hi>Father,</hi> and the authority of the <hi>Word,</hi> to bear wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes that he was ſent of God, &amp; propheſied of old to be the <hi>Meſſias, John</hi> 5.31.32.37.46. &amp; 8.17.18. Alſo the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> when he was queſtioned by his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies about his authority, or the lawfulnes of his office, he goes unto his <hi>Call</hi> into his office, and that authority that placed him in it, and by that proves, that he tooke not that authority that he exerciſed upon him without good grounds, but had it placed upon him by <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> himſelfe, <hi>Acts</hi> 22.10.11. &amp; ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. Alſo when he was queſtioned by the falſe Apoſtles at <hi>Corinth</hi> and <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latia</hi> about his authority, he anſwers for himſelfe, that he was an Apoſtle, and was free, for I have (ſaith he ſeen Jeſus Chriſt) who placed me in my office, and by his authority gave me my <hi>Apoſtleſhip,</hi> and called me by his voyce there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, ſo that my authority, and calling is not from men (as you falſe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles are, nor by men, (as the Ordinary Officers of the Church are, who are called by the Church, who hath authority from God ſo to doe) but immediately from Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, as all his true Apoſtels are, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.1. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.1. So that you ſee <hi>Paul</hi> proved he was an Apoſtle, and a true officer of Jeſus Chriſt, before ever he preached his Goſpell, and before ever he was an inſtrument to bring any to the knowledge and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the truth, and before ever the <hi>Corinthes</hi> became (being begot by his Miniſtery) the Seale of his Apoſtleſhip. And doth <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> Chriſt, and his Apoſtles whenſoever they are queſtioned about their authority by their op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers, prove their calling into their office, by virtue of which they doe offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate, and adminiſter thoſe adminiſtrations they adminiſter? and thinke your Miniſters thoſe Preiſts and Deacons of Antichriſt to have more exemption then Chriſt or his Apoſtles had? and therefore if they be miniſters of Chriſt (as they ſay they are) I put you and them upon it to prove their calling and office from him, that they were inſtated into their Miniſtry by virtue of his power and Lawes: which he hath left recorded in his laſt Will and Teſtament for the bodies of his particular viſible Churches to elect, chuſe, and ordaine their owne Officers: either let them doe this, or elſe I ſay, and will againſt them all main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it, that they are Antichriſts Miniſters, ſet in by the power of Satan in the
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:154971:11"/>
Kingdome of the <hi>ſeaven headed, and ten horned Beaſt</hi> in direct oppoſition, and profeſſed hatred <hi>againſt the Kingdome and Septer of Jeſus Chriſt the eternall S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n of God,</hi> for they are but falſe Prophets, falſe Shee Pheards, and falſe Teachers, like thoſe in <hi>Jeremiahs</hi> time, <hi>that runne before ever God ſent them, and ſay they are of his ſending, when as indeed thiy lye, Jer.</hi> 14.14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 23.21.32 <hi>Ezeck.</hi> 18.6.7. <hi>for he never ſent any of them, Rev.</hi> 9.3. Therefore doe you, and all thoſe that are under their Jurisdiction looke to it, as they and you love your owne ſoules: for the Lord hath not only threatned to plague falſe Prophets, falſe Miniſters, and falſe ſheepheards, but alſo all thoſe that give care and ſubmit unto them, and are ſeduced by them, <hi>Eſa</hi> 9.16. <hi>Jer.</hi> 14.15.16. &amp; 23.15.16.34.39. &amp; 27.15. &amp; 29.8.9.18. <hi>Ezeck.</hi> 13.8.9.10. So that it is not enough for a man that takes upon him to be a Prophet, and a Sheepheard to come in the name of the Lord, and doe part of thoſe things which a true Prophet, and Sheepheard of the Lord doth; but firſt of all he muſt prove his Authority, and that he is of the Lords ſending, elſe none of Chriſts Sheep are to give eare unto him, <hi>John</hi> 10. <hi>the beginning;</hi> for Chriſt hath bid them beware of ſuch, ſeeing many of them were, and ſtill a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e to come abroad into the World, coming in ſuch a foule deceiving flattering way, <hi>that they ſhould deceive if it were poſſible the very Elect, Mat.</hi> 7.15. <hi>&amp;</hi> 24.11.24. <hi>Mar.</hi> 13.22.23. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. 1 <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hn.</hi> 4.1. and the reaſon wherefore they ſhould beware of them, and try, and examine their Authority from whence it is, as the Church of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>eſus</hi> did, for which ſhe is highly commended, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. is becauſe that falſe Apoſtles, and falſe miniſters, all of them are deceitfull workers, tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming themſelves into the Apoſtles of Chriſt and miniſters of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. <hi>Therefore all Gods people had need exceedingly to labour for true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and underſtanding is it is their duty, that ſo they may be able to try, and know falſe Miniſters, and Sheepeards from true ones, leaſt their ſoules run vpon the Rockes, and ſo be in great danger of ſuffering ſhipwrake in ſubmitting and giving <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eare unto thoſe Miniſters, and Preachers that never were of the Lords ſending, nor never received their errand from him in the number of which are all the Miniſters in England, as well the beſt as the worſt, done of them being Chriſts true Miniſters, but Antichriſts Locuſts, which came out of the ſmoake of the bottomleſſe pit, and are fully deſcribed in the ninth of the Revelation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I know what evation you will have to prove your <hi>Biſhops, Preiſts, and Deacons,</hi> true, which is to fetch, and derive their lineall ſucceſſion <hi>(which Rabby Pocklington in his Sunday no Sabboth boaſts of)</hi> from his <hi>impiety of Rome,</hi> that <hi>Antichriſt and man of Sin, and Son of Perdition,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.3. and ſo thinke to avoyde all that I have ſaid againſt them, and alſo you will rune to your greaſie mouldy Conſecration, and laying on hands, by which you give them your own Holy Ghoſt, namely the ſpirit of errour, of blindneſſe and ignorance, and therefore if you goe to the Pope
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:154971:11"/>
and derive their authority from him: as of abſolute neceſſity you muſt, this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your beſt, and only Argument you have to prove them true, which <hi>Maſon</hi> to the utmoſt makes uſe of againſt the Papiſts, who deny your Biſhops, Preiſts and Deacons to be true ones, becauſe you ſchiſmed away from them, and ſo they want Cannonicall Ordination (as they call it) and therefore <hi>Maſon</hi> in his booke of Ordination of Biſhops, Preiſts and Deacons, proves it at large to be a falſe accuſation, and that they are true having, had an inviolable cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall Ordination and Conſecration from the Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> as there you may largly read, <hi>pag.</hi> 10. 41. 58. 62. 64. 88. <hi>and ſo forward to the end:</hi> Now if you goe this way to worke too, as of neceſſity you muſt, having no other way, at all to goe to prove them true, then what doe you elſe but even you your ſelfe, prove your Miniſters to be Antichriſtian, whom <hi>Maſon</hi> in his fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Booke, <hi>pag.</hi> 77 doth prove by the authority of the Scripture, that if they be ſo, it is the duty of all Gods people to ſeperate from them: And as for <hi>laying on of hands,</hi> I ſay it was but a Ceremony, which ceaſed when the viſible working of miracles ceaſed, which if you ſay to the contrary, I put you upon it, to prove it, a durable and permanent action in the Church of God, abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely eſſentiall to the making of a true <hi>Paſtor, Teacher, Elder or Biſhop:</hi> Alſo you will ſay, one miniſter muſt make an other, but your miniſters and officers are made by other miniſters and officers, therefore they are true: But I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that either he that is made, or he that made your miniſters is true: But for the Argument, I abſolutely deny the propoſition, and I affirme that it is not eſſentiall to the makeing of a true Biſhop or elder, (which is all one, <hi>Titus</hi> 1. to be made by other <hi>Biſhops</hi> or <hi>Elders,</hi> for thoſe <hi>Biſhops, Elders</hi> and <hi>Deacons,</hi> that were made in the Apoſtles times, were elected and made by the Church, who only hath power for that end, and the Apoſtles and Evangeliſts did no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe by that action of <hi>laying on of hand,</hi> but ſhew their likeing and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of that action that the Church had performed, and of thoſe perſons that the Church had made Officers, to officiate in her, and at the <hi>laying on of the Apoſtles hands,</hi> God was pleaſed to worke miracles, even to give the Holy Ghoſt unto thoſe upon whom they was layd, which were no officers in the Church, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.17.18. &amp; 19.6. and alſo at the curing the Father of <hi>Publius</hi> of his Feaver, <hi>Paul</hi> laid his hands upon him and healed him, <hi>Acts</hi> 28.8. yea <hi>Ananias</hi> who was no officer in the Church but a <hi>Diſciple</hi> or a private man (as you call them) yet he laid his hands upon <hi>Saul,</hi> at the doing of which he received his ſight, and alſo the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.20.17. So that you ſee <hi>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ying on of hands in</hi> the primative time, was not only peculiar to the Apoſtles and Evangeliſts themſelves, bat alſo to others which were no offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, but Brethren, out of office, and was not only uſed at the ſhewing their approbation and likeing of thoſe men that the Church had choſen into office, but alſo at the workeing of miracles, as the giving of the Holy Ghoſt,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:154971:12"/>
and healing of the <hi>Sicke,</hi> ſo that I affirme, that <hi>Action</hi> ceaſed when the viſible working of <hi>Miracles</hi> ceaſed, and is not in the leaſt eſſentiall to the making of <hi>Officers.</hi> Againe, in the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> you doe not find, neither are you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to prove or ſhew one example that an <hi>Apoſtle</hi> was made by anorher <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> or that on? <hi>Evangeliſt</hi> was made by another <hi>Evangeliſt,</hi> or that one <hi>Biſhop</hi> or <hi>Elder</hi> was made by another <hi>Biſhop</hi> or <hi>Elder,</hi> or ever that one <hi>Officer</hi> made ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Officer</hi> in the ſame <hi>Office</hi> that he himſelfe was in: ſo that your making of <hi>Biſhops</hi> by other <hi>Biſhops</hi> is an <hi>Invention</hi> of the <hi>Man</hi> of <hi>Sinne,</hi> and his <hi>Fellowes,</hi> therefore to make <hi>Officers</hi> by <hi>Officers</hi> will never be proved by you nor any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, to be <hi>Eſſentiall</hi> to the making of an <hi>Officer,</hi> and therefore I ſay of your <hi>Officers,</hi> that both the <hi>makars and thoſe that are made by them,</hi> are all of them falſe, not only in regard this action is a ſiction of your owne Invention, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo becauſe your Church is falſe and <hi>Antichriſtian. Therefore if every</hi> Pariſh <hi>in</hi> England <hi>had power in themſelves (which in the leaſt they have not) to chuſe and make their owne</hi> Officers, <hi>yet for all this they would be falſe, for a falſe and</hi> Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian <hi>Church as yours is, can never make true</hi> Officers <hi>and</hi> Miniſters <hi>of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt: <hi>and though that the Churches of the</hi> Seperation <hi>want the</hi> Apoſtles <hi>in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall preſence to lay hands upon their Officers which lawfully they chuſe out from among themſeves, yet have they their Lawes, Rules and Directions in writing, which is their</hi> Office, <hi>and is of as great Authority as their perſonall preſence.</hi> Mat. 7.12. Luk. 16.29.31 Joh. 5.45. Act. 13.27. &amp; 15.21. &amp; 21.21. 2. Cor. 3.15. <hi>All theſe writings doth ſhew that the Scriptures &amp; Lawes of</hi> Moſes <hi>&amp; the</hi> Prophets <hi>was their</hi> Office, <hi>for they themſelves were dead long before</hi> Chriſts <hi>time, but their writings did ſtill remaine, wherefore the ſpirit of</hi> God <hi>is pleaſed to call them by their names, ſhewong that they are of as great Authority as their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall preſence were, and thoſe that now read them if they doe not obey them, is as inexcuſable as thoſe that lived in their daies &amp; heard them from their mouthes and yet rejected them.</hi> Even ſo now though we have not <hi>Peter</hi> &amp; <hi>Paul</hi> &amp; the reſt of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> in perſonall preſence, yet we have now their <hi>Lawes, Rules, Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles</hi> &amp; <hi>directions</hi> which they ſent &amp; gave to the Churches of <hi>God</hi> that was planted in their times, &amp; theſe are there <hi>Office,</hi> &amp; are of as great <hi>Authority</hi> &amp; <hi>Suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency</hi> as their perſonall preſence, yea and of greater, as the very falſe <hi>Apoſtles</hi> themſelves thoſe enemies of Paul doe confeſſe <hi>for his letters ſay they are waigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty &amp; powerfull, but his bodily preſence is weake &amp; his ſpeech contemptible.</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.10. For Paul in the writing of the <hi>Scripture</hi> was ſo powerfully guided by the Spirit of <hi>God</hi> that it was not poſſible for him to erre in the doing of it, whereas in his other perſonall actions he was ſubject to ſin &amp; failings as well as Peter was <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.11. &amp; the reſt of the <hi>Apoſtles:</hi> ſome of which we read of <hi>Act.</hi> 22. which was his going into the <hi>Temple</hi> with others, after the <hi>Ceremoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Law of Moſes</hi> to purifie himſelfe, when he knew his <hi>Lord</hi> &amp; <hi>Maſter Chriſt</hi> at his death had aboliſhed and put an end both to the <hi>Temple</hi> &amp; all the <hi>Moſaica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Rites
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:154971:12"/>
Ceremonies</hi> &amp; <hi>Worſhip,</hi> and he himſelfe with the reſt of the <hi>Apoſtles Act.</hi> 15. but the Spirit of God had decreed the ſame, which they commanded the Churches inviolably to obſerve, and alſo he himſelfe before did preach the ſame, ſo that I ſay the Apoſtes Lawes is their office, and is of as great, yea greater authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty then if now we had them in perſonall being: therefore in my judgement thoſe that doe maintaine Apoſtles now in perſonall being, doe maintaine an errour, ſeing that the <hi>Apoſtle Paul</hi> calls himſelfe and <hi>Barnabas</hi> the laſt, as it were men apoynted to death. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.9. &amp; if they were the laſt then none were to follow or ſucceed them in their <hi>Office,</hi> therefore your <hi>Biſhops</hi> are all Liars, in calling themſelves the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> ſucceſſours, for they are <hi>Antichriſts Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſts &amp; Frogges which are ſaid to come out of the ſmoke of the bottommleſſe pot, or out of the mouth of the Dragon, Beaſt &amp; falſe Prophet Rev.</hi> 9.3. &amp; 16.13. So that I affirme the <hi>Officers</hi> in the true Churches of the <hi>Sepearion,</hi> that are called by virtue of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> Lawes, though they want them to lay hands upon them, to ſhew their aprobation of their fitneſſe for their <hi>Office,</hi> yet they are as true <hi>Officers</hi> as thoſe that they themſelves cauſed to be made, and laid their hands upon.</p>
            <p>And thus have I ſufficiently by the authority of the ſacred word of God proved all your Officers &amp; Miniſters, falſe &amp; <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> &amp; none of Chriſts, which if you can groundedly contradict, ſhew your beſt skill challeng I you, &amp; put you to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> prop to hold up your tottering &amp; ſandy Ch. &amp; Min. or elſe your great brags will prove no better then wind and fables, and you, your ſelfe found to be a liar.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Againe in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he ſecond place if your Preiſts by their miniſtery do not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh the ſame ends, that the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> by their <hi>miniſtery</hi> did, then by your own grounds they are no true <hi>Miniſters</hi> of Chriſt: and that they doe not by their miniſtery accompliſh the ſame ends, that the <hi>Miniſtery</hi> of the Apoſtles did, I prove it out of the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2. where the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> doth praiſe the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> that they did remember him in all things, &amp; keep all the ordinances as he had delivered them unto them; here was one maine end that the <hi>Miniſtery</hi> of the <hi>Apoſt.</hi> did accompliſh; namely to bring the Saints in the ch. of God to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience not only of ſome but of all the Lawes of Chriſt, but your Miniſtery never did, never will, nor never can, ſo long as they ſtand in their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent calling, and office accompliſh this end, in the heart: &amp; lives of thoſe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:154971:13"/>
that heare and give eare vnto them, but rather by their Miniſtery they teach them flat Rebellion to the Lawes and Ordinances of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As firſt Chriſt is not only the alone <hi>Preiſt</hi> of his Church and people to reconcile them by his blood to God his Father, but alſo he is the alone and only <hi>Prophet</hi> of his Church, to whom alone they are to goe for counſell and knowledge, and to whoſe voyce only they are to give eare, and to no other Prophet, and this did his Apoſtles teach his people to obſerve, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.22.23. <hi>for Moſes truly ſaid unto your Fathers, a Prophet ſhall the Lord God raiſe up unto you of your Brethren like vnto me him ſhall you heare in all things what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he ſhall ſay vnto you, and it ſhall come to paſſe, that every ſoul that will not heare that</hi> Prophet <hi>ſhall be deſtroyed from among the people,</hi> and <hi>Gal.</hi> 5, 1, there <hi>Paul</hi> bids them <hi>ſtand faſt in the</hi> Liberty <hi>wherewith</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>hath made us free and b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t againe entangled in the yoke of bondage.</hi> And in his giving Lawes to the Corinthians, he would have them follow him no further then he follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Chriſt</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.1. But your <hi>Miniſters</hi> in their actions and practiſe do declare and ſay unto the people that they will not owne <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> for the only <hi>Prophet</hi> or his Church. and therefore they teach the people to worſhip the Lord with Ceremonies, and <hi>Wil-worſhip,</hi> as <hi>Capping, Cringing</hi> and <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king,</hi> clean contrary to the ſeccond Commandement: and alſo with <hi>Holy G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> as they call them, and with booke prayer tranſlated out of the <hi>Popes</hi> curſed <hi>Maſſe-booke,</hi> as worthy Dr. <hi>Euſtaricke</hi> doeth in the third part of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s <hi>Letany,</hi> declare and prove: by which they teach the people to leave the naked <hi>ſimplicity</hi> of that worſhip, which <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> hath inſtituted in his <hi>New Teſtament, John</hi> 4.23.25. ſaying to the <hi>woman</hi> of <hi>Samaria, the hower cometh and now is,</hi> when the true worſhippers ſhall worſhip the Father in ſpirit and in truth; for the Father ſeeketh ſuch to worſhip him, <hi>for God is a ſpirit, and they that worſhip rim, muſt worſhip him in ſpirit and in truth;</hi> and tie, and bring the people to <hi>worſhip God,</hi> with a <hi>worſhip</hi> which is meerly and altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſinfull, mens inventions and fooliſh deviſes, which worſhip is odious, deteſtable, hatefull, abominable to God, <hi>Eſa</hi> 1.11.12.13. &amp; 66.3.4. <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.19.20. &amp; 25.6.44.21.22.23. <hi>Amos</hi> 5.21.22. <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.8.9. <hi>Marke</hi> 7.7.8. <hi>Col.</hi> 2. So that I may truly ſay, of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and the worſhippers therein, as the ſpirit of God ſaid of <hi>Judah</hi> in the ſecond of <hi>Eſa</hi> 8.9. <hi>their Land alſo is full of Idols, they worſhip the workes of their owne hands, that which their owne fingers have made, and the meane man boweth downe, and the great man humbleth himſelfe; therefore forgive them not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Againe in the third place, as Jeſus Chriſt is the only <hi>Preiſt,</hi> and <hi>Porphet</hi> of his Church, ſo he is the only <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Lawgiver</hi> of it, and to it, and none elſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. &amp; 149.19. <hi>Eſa</hi> 9.6.7. &amp; 83.20. for the Lord is our Judge, the Lord is our Lawgiver, (ſaith the Church of God) the Lord is our King,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:154971:13"/>
he will ſave us? now the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> by their <hi>miniſtery</hi> taught this to the <hi>Saints,</hi> and <hi>Churches</hi> of <hi>God, That Jeſus Chriſt is the only King, and Lawgiver of, and to his Church, vnto whoſe Lawes and Septer alone, and to none other they muſt ſtoope, ſubmit, and yeild unto, Epheſ.</hi> 1.21.22. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2.22.23. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.2.3.6.7. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3. <hi>begin. &amp;</hi> 20.28.29. <hi>&amp;</hi> 12.25.</p>
            <p>But your <hi>Miniſters</hi> by their <hi>Miniſtrery</hi> teach the people <hi>to rebell and bid de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance againſt the Septer, Lawes, and Commands of Chriſt,</hi> as though he had not had wiſedome and power enough, to have erected and governed his owne ſpirituall Kingdome, and to have inſtituted ſufficient Offices as voyd places for his people, by virtue of his Lawes to elect and chuſe Officers to adminiſter, therin for the building of them up, till they come to perfect then in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, <hi>and unto the meaſure of the fulnes of Chriſt;</hi> contrary to what the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> affirmes by the ſpirit of God, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.11.12.13. and therefore they teach the people to run to <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> and ſeeke for more Officers: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with ſuch horrible wickednes as this which your <hi>Biſhops, Preiſts, and Deacens,</hi> thoſe <hi>litle toes</hi> of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> dayly, and howerly perpetrate and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, as if ſo be Jeſus Chriſt had not been ſo faithfull in <hi>his Houſe, as Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes was in his,</hi> and as though he had not had ſo ſufficient a care of his Church under the Goſpell, as <hi>Moſes</hi> had under the Law, and therefore they goe unto <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> Chriſts <hi>profeſſed enemie,</hi> and there would teach the people to ſeeke for Lawes for the governing of the Church of God under the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, rakeing them out of his <hi>curſed counſels, Bookes of Articles, and diabolicall Traditions,</hi> and in their doing of this, which is their conſtant practiſes, they teach flat Rebellion, and High Treaſon againg the <hi>Septer</hi> and <hi>Kingdome</hi> of the <hi>everlaſting Son of God,</hi> who will have his <hi>church</hi> governed by his owne <hi>Lawes, which he inſtituted, and left recorded in his laſt Will and Teſtament, which he hath bequeathed to his church, commanding them, as they will anſwer it before his dreadfull appearing, to obſerve and keep them ſtrictly without violati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the leaſt;</hi> and alſo by his owne Officers therein expreſſed, <hi>who are only five,</hi> who are to be <hi>permanent, officiating in perſonall preſence and Being</hi> for the <hi>freedome of his church;</hi> namely, <hi>Paſtor, Teocher, Elder, Deacon, and Widdow, Rom.</hi> 12.7.8. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.1. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5. <hi>chap.</hi> But they teach the people <hi>to goe to the Lawes, and Officers of Antichriſt, which are a great multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude in number, as, Patriarkes, Primates, Metrapolitanes, Arch-Biſhops, Lord Biſhops, Deanes, Chancellours, Vicar generall, Prebends, Doctours of the Civill Law, Doctours of Divinity, Proctours, Regiſters, Arch-Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, Sub-Deacons, Preiſts, Jeſuites, Pariſh-preiſts, Parſons, Vicars, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, Cannons, Petty Cannons, Chanters, Veſtrey men, Church wardens Sworne men, Side men, Pariſh clarkes, damnable and diveliſh Purſevants, Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, Apparritours, with a great many more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore in this reſpect <hi>doe not by their Miniſtery accompliſh the ſame</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:154971:14"/>
ends that the <hi>Miniſtery of the Apoſtles did,</hi> and ſo by your owne grounds are <hi>no true Miniſters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for thoſe two things, <hi>of converſion, and confirmation, or building up in the wayes of God,</hi> which you ſpeake of, if you meane by <hi>converſion, an opening of the eyes, to turne them from drunkenes to light, and from the power of Satan unto God:</hi> Or if you meane, by <hi>converſion, a deliverance from the power of darkenes, and a tranſlation into the Kingdome of the Son of God,</hi> both of which the <hi>Apoſtles Miniſtery</hi> did <hi>accompliſh</hi> in the <hi>hearts</hi> and <hi>lives of Gods people, Asts</hi> 26.18. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.13. I abſolutely deny it, that <hi>your Miniſtery</hi> in <hi>England</hi> doth this: And therefore I deſire you to declare, what you meane by <hi>converſion,</hi> and prove your definition by the <hi>holy Scripture</hi> and alſo prove that you in England are <hi>ſo converted,</hi> which when you have done, I ſhall further anſwer you, <hi>by Gods aſſiſtance.</hi> And as for their <hi>building them up in the wayes of God</hi> as all true Sheepheards ought to build, up their ſheepe, as <hi>Acts</hi> 20. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. yet I deny it, that <hi>your miniſters</hi> doe it, for <hi>how can they build them vp in that which they themſelves are ignorant of, and enemies unto;</hi> for as <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres which withſtood Moſes,</hi> ſo doe theſe men alſo reſiſt the truth, being men of corrupt minds, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of the truth, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.8. <hi>and doe feed you with huskes and chaffe, being neither willing to embrace it themſelves, nor to let thoſe that would,</hi> as their conſtant preaching and ſpeaking againſt the truth, of <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of his Son</hi> doth witneſſe.</p>
            <p>And in the <hi>concluſion</hi> of this your Argument, you ſay, when the <hi>Separati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> can prove <hi>converſion</hi> in an Antichriſtian Church, you will ſay more to them; this belongs to you to prove, <hi>for we doe not plead for Antichriſt, but againſt him, and all his:</hi> And therefore have I taken the paines by the <hi>Word of God, and demonſtrable Argument grounded therevpon, to prove the Church of</hi> England <hi>Antichriſtian:</hi> And when you or any other <hi>doe</hi> by the <hi>Authority</hi> of the unerring and pure <hi>Word of God,</hi> ſufficiently <hi>confute</hi> what I have writ againſt it, <hi>I doe promiſe you, I will be a member of the Church of</hi> England <hi>againe;</hi> but if that be not done, <hi>I will by the ſtrength of the Lord of Hoſts for ever ſeparate from Church, Miniſtery, and worſhip in</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>as all and every one of them Antichriſtean and falſe:</hi> yet thus much I ſay, and doe acknowledge, and the Scripture <hi>proves it,</hi> that <hi>God hath a people or an elect number in ſpirituall Babylon, yea in the Kingdome of Antichriſt, part of which the</hi> ch. <hi>of</hi> England <hi>is, and none of them ſhall periſh, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e eternally ſaved:</hi> yet I ſay, <hi>it is the duty of all Gods Elect &amp; choſen ones, that as yet in the whoriſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> of the</hi> ch. <hi>of</hi> Engl. <hi>or in any part of Antichriſts regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſeparate away from it, and come out of it, leaſt God plague them for their ſtaying there, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> forward, &amp;</hi> 51.6.9.11. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16.17. <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.9.10. <hi>&amp;</hi> 18.4. Now from all that which hath been ſaid, I frame theſe Arguments
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:154971:14"/>
               <hi>Firſt that every lawfull Paſtor, Biſhop, Miniſter, or Officer in the viſible Church of Chriſt ought to have a lawfull call, and be lawfully choſen into his Office, before he can be a true Officer in the Church of Chriſt, Acts</hi> 1.24.25. <hi>&amp;</hi> 26. <hi>&amp;</hi> 24.23. <hi>Gal.</hi> 
               <hi rend="sup">c</hi> 11. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But the Miniſters and Officers in the Church of</hi> England <hi>have not a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full call, neither are lawfully choſen to be Officers in the Church of Chriſt</hi> ſee the Booke of Ordination of Biſhops, Preiſts, and Deacons compared with the Scripture.</p>
            <p>Therefore, <hi>all your Miniſters are falſe and Antichriſtian Officers, Rev.</hi> 9.3. 2. Secondly, <hi>The doing of thoſe actions that belong to the execution of an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, doth not prove a man to be a lawfull officer, but a lawfull power inſtating him into his office, Acts</hi> 8.4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 11.28.24. <hi>&amp;</hi> 18.24.26.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But all the Miniſters in the</hi> church <hi>of</hi> England <hi>have nothing to prove the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes of their ſtanding in their Miniſtery, but the actions of a Miniſter, and are not able to prove that they are inſtated into their Miniſtery, by vertue of a lawfull power and authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore, <hi>they are not true Miniſters of Chriſt, but falſe and Antichriſtian Miniſters of Antichriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Againe in the third place upon your own grounds I frame this Argument. <hi>Thoſe that by their Miniſtery doe not accompliſh the ſame ends, that the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery of the Apoſtles did, are no true miniſters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But the miniſters of the</hi> church <hi>of</hi> England <hi>doe not accompliſh the ſame ends by their miniſtery, that the miniſtery of the Apoſtles did,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.2.</p>
            <p>Therefore, <hi>your miniſters are no true miniſters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So you ſee I have overthrown your ſecond Argument, and that in your own way, and deny that which I have ſaid, and prove againſt it if you be able.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Againe your 3. Arg. to prove your ſcratched and deformed mother a true viſible church is this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whatſoever people doe enjoy &amp; outwardly ſubmit themſelves to the true worſhip of God, they are a true viſible ch. of Chriſt. But the people of</hi> Eng. <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e outwardly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy and ſubmit themſelves to the true worſhip of God.</hi> Ergo <hi>the people of</hi> England <hi>are a true viſible Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 3. And for the proofe of your Arg. you ſay that the Separation grant and teach the propoſition, but the aſſupmtion they ſtifly deny (as well they may do) but you will ſtifly maintaine, and prove it to their ſhame But firſt of all I will prove your Arg. falſe to your ſhame, and then I will examine your proofe of it: Therefore I deny your propoſition, aſſumption, and concluſion. And firſt you ſay the Separation teach where there is true worſhip, there is a true Church, what they teach I doe not very well know, for I never heard any of their Sermons, but only one, neither have I read but very few either of their <hi>Books</hi> or <hi>writings;</hi> but yet I ſay your <hi>Major</hi> is not found, for true worſhip doth not prove a <hi>company</hi> of <hi>people,</hi> to be a true <hi>viſible church</hi> of Chriſt, for they muſt be a true <hi>viſible church</hi> before they ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:154971:15"/>
and offer up any publike worſhip to him: therefore true worſhip doth not prov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a <hi>true church,</hi> but rather a <hi>true church</hi> proves <hi>true worſhip,</hi> for the <hi>cauſe muſt ever goe before the effect</hi> which it produceth; but a true Church produceth true worſhip, and not true worſhip a true Church: Now to the makeing of a true Church, there muſt not only be <hi>true matter,</hi> but alſo a <hi>true forme,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.13. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.5. or an entrance into that heavenly ſtate, or <hi>ſpirituall city,</hi> called the <hi>New Jeruſalem, which comes downe from heaven,</hi> and which is (in the laſt end) deſcribed in the Word of God, and ſo becoming a <hi>politike Kingdome</hi> or Body that makes them a <hi>true church;</hi> or an <hi>vniting, joyning,</hi> or <hi>combining</hi> of a <hi>company of Beleivers</hi> together amongſt themſelves, and ſo unto Chriſt <hi>their only and alone head and King,</hi> promiſing perfect obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to all his Lawes, and to walke in all his wayes, that gives them the <hi>denomination</hi> of a <hi>true viſible church</hi> of Chriſt, by virtue of which they come to have Chriſts power to execute all the Lawes that Jeſus Chriſt hath left and bequeathed in his <hi>laſt will</hi> to his <hi>welbeloved Spouſe,</hi> and to <hi>adminiſter</hi> all his <hi>adminiſtrations,</hi> which out of this ſtate cannot lawfully be <hi>adminiſtred:</hi> as I have already proved at large in my <hi>Anſwer</hi> to <hi>W. G.</hi> an <hi>eminent Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in your Church, but yet an <hi>earneſt pleader</hi> for <hi>Antichriſts Kingdome</hi> and <hi>dominion,</hi> as well as your ſelfe, and therefore for this particular I referre you to that.</p>
            <p>And as for your <hi>Minor</hi> and <hi>Aſſumption,</hi> which is that you in the Church of <hi>England</hi> doe enjoy, and outwardly ſubmit your ſelves to the true worſhip of God: It is moſt falſe and a notorious, lie and untruth, and as well might wicked <hi>Faux,</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Gun-pouder plotters</hi> ſay, that they ſubmitted unto noble King <hi>James</hi> Lawes and Septer, when they went about to blow up the Parliament Houſe, that ſo they might deſtroy him and all his; for you doe not only oppoſe, and juſtle out the true worſhip of God, and throw downe and trample upon the Septer of Jeſus Chriſt his Son, but alſo you ſet up a falſe and Antichriſtian worſhip, the inventer of which is the Divel, and the <hi>man of Sin,</hi> his eldeſt and moſt obedient Son: Therefore I am aſhamed to heare you who boaſt your ſelfe to be ſuch a mighty champion, as you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay you are (having as I heare you have ſaid, that you have confuted many of the <hi>Separation</hi>) to reaſon ſo ſhallowly and ungroundedly, and againſt the knowne and confeſſed truth and therefore you are but like <hi>Goliah</hi> the <hi>Philiſtins</hi> great champion, who exceedingly reviled as you doe, the <hi>Hoaſt</hi> of <hi>the Lord,</hi> and kept a mighty challinging of them, as though none of <hi>Gods people</hi> had been able to encounter and graple with him; when as poore <hi>David</hi> that yongue ſtripling with his ſheepheards ſtaffe and a company of ſmooth ſtones flung out of a ſlinge overcame and deſtroyed that mighty Giant, who thought none ſo ſtronge as himſelfe, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. and juſtifieth an one are you, and will prove to be, for you fight for the ſpirituall <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtims,</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:154971:15"/>
the enemies of the Lord, namely for Antichriſt, and his Kingdome, and you ſend forth great bragges &amp; boaſtes againſt the truth of God amongſt your ignorant acquaintance, but indeed they are nothing but wind and chaffe not able to ſtand before the breath of Gods ſacred truth, which his weake ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants for their conquering weapons make uſe of, as I have already, and ſhall more fully by the ſtrength of God make it appeare in my following lines, and therefore to confute your Argument, and lay it even with the ground, I will bring your owne Writers weapons, who were members in the Church of England, who doe not plead for Separation, but for Reformation therein read but the <hi>Lincolne-ſhire Miniſters Abridgment,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Cartwrights Defence againſt Biſhop Whiteguift,</hi> ſometime <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Lambeth,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Ames</hi> his <hi>Freſh Suite againſt Humaine Ceremonies,</hi> and you ſhall ſee your worſhip proved to be Antichriſtian, and none of Chriſts, but of the Divels invention. Alſo read the <hi>Scots Diſpute</hi> printed in <hi>Holland</hi> the laſt Summer, and you ſhall ſee the greateſt part of your worſhip, and all your humaine Ceremonies, with which you ſerve God, proved to be Idols, as your <hi>holy garments,</hi> and your invented geſtures of <hi>bowing,</hi> and <hi>cringing,</hi> and your <hi>kneling</hi> at the act of receiving the <hi>Sacrament,</hi> &amp;c. Alſo read a litle Booke of Mr. <hi>Damfords</hi> (ſometime Miniſter of <hi>Colmanſtreet</hi> in <hi>London</hi>) againſt the Service. And noble Dr. <hi>Baſtwickes</hi> book called <hi>The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>anity and Impiety of the old Letany.</hi> and you ſhall ſee the <hi>Wickednes, Sinfulnes</hi> and <hi>Vngodlines of it</hi> ſet forth to the utmoſt, for there it is proved to be an Idoll, which as he there faith, ſends more ſoules to Hell in a yeare then all the prophaneneſſe, deboyſtneſſe, wickedneſſe and ungodlynes in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome doth beſides, and that nothing could have been invented either by the Divell, or the Pope, for a greater meanes to pull downe the Kingdome of Chriſt, and for the maintaining and building up the Kingdome of Antichriſt, and therefore I put you upon it to Anſwer their writings, and confute the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments of your own Authors, which have fully proved that your worſhip is no divine but humane worſhip, and therefore not a true but a falſe worſhip.</p>
            <p>Now if you ſhould deny that your humaine invented diabollicall Booke of Common prayer, and your ſacred Ceremonies (as your Lords and maſters the Biſhops cals them) are not the worſhip, with which you in the Church of England worſhip and ſerve God, the Booke of Common prayer it ſelfe will confute you, for there in the Preface before that Booke of deviſed Service, and wicked mans invention they aſcribe to the dumbe Ceremonies, a Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall naature, and the very Office, and worke of the ſpirit of God, the doing of which makes them all to become Idols, and all thoſe Idolaters that uſe them, or partake with them that doe it, for there they ſay, they are apt to ſtirre up the dull mind of man to the remembrance of his duty to God by ſome notable and ſpeaciall ſignification whereby he might be edefied: Alſo in the act of vnifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:154971:16"/>
they themſelves doe confeſſe that they are but of mans Invention, and device, and to worſhip God with mans devices and Inventions, is odious and deteſtable unto him, as before I have fully proved: and therefore you in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> have not the true <hi>Worſhip</hi> of God, and ſo by your owne confeſſion are not a true Church of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now to anſwer your Argument which you bring to prove your <hi>Aſſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> which is this: <hi>You have had thoſe that have lived and dyed in the ſame Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip which you ſtill have, and have beene ſaved in it, therefore it muſt needes be a true Worſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This you ſay, but doe not prove it in the leaſt, but ſtill take that for granted which I deny; which is, that it doth not therefore follow becauſe ſome in the Church of <hi>England</hi> have been ſaved that have uſed your <hi>Worſhip,</hi> that therfore it is true <hi>Worſhip,</hi> for then it would follow that the <hi>Worſhip</hi> in the <hi>Papiſtry,</hi> which in ſome reſpects is more groſſer then yours, is a true <hi>Worſhip,</hi> for you dare not deny it, which if you doe, you are not able to prove it, that in the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtry</hi> there hath not beene many people that have lived and died therein that have been ſaved, for the <hi>Scripture</hi> doth declare that <hi>God</hi> hath a people there, which he calls uppon to come out thence. <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.4. for he ownes his <hi>Elect</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in <hi>Spirituall Babilon:</hi> yet for all this it doth not follow that their <hi>Worſhip</hi> is or ever was a true <hi>Worſhip,</hi> though the <hi>Riches</hi> of the <hi>Grace,</hi> and <hi>unfathomable Goodnes</hi> of the <hi>Kindnes and Love of God</hi> doth reach and extend ſo far as to ſave ſome that live and dy in that <hi>Worſhip</hi> as well as in the <hi>Worſhip</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> yet I ſay it is as extraordinary a worke as the manifeſtation of <hi>Gods</hi> love to the <hi>Thiefe</hi> upon the <hi>Croſſe</hi> was, but for all that, <hi>I</hi> will maintaine it, that none of thoſe that yeild and ſubmit themſelves unto your or their <hi>Worſhip,</hi> cannot by the <hi>Scripture</hi> prove himſelfe to be a viſible <hi>Chriſtian</hi> or a true beleever, if they ſhould be put (by Gods people) to prove it. <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.21.23.24. <hi>&amp;</hi> 15.8.14. <hi>Col.</hi> 15.19 <hi>to the end. Eph,</hi> 5.8. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.21. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.16. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2.14. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2, 9. <hi>Heb</hi> 9.14. <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.17, 18. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.8. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2 <hi>Joh.</hi> 9. <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.8. <hi>&amp;</hi> 14.1.4.9.10. <hi>&amp;</hi> 19.20.</p>
            <p>Now from that which I have ſaid <hi>I</hi> frame theſe Arguments.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>That Worſhip which is of the</hi> Divells <hi>and</hi> Antichriſts <hi>Invention, Inſtitution &amp; ſetting up, is no true divine</hi> Worſhip.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But the</hi> Worſhip <hi>of the Church of</hi> England <hi>is of the</hi> Divells <hi>&amp;</hi> Antichriſts <hi>Invention, Inſtitution &amp; ſetting up, as the forenamed Authors, and the</hi> 13. <hi>Chap of the Rev. doth fully prove.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ergo. <hi>The</hi> Worſhip <hi>in the</hi> Church <hi>of</hi> England <hi>is no true</hi> Morſhip.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That</hi> Worſhip <hi>which is a main meanes &amp; cauſe of pulling downe the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>&amp; eſtabliſhing, maintaining &amp; upholding of the Kingdome of the</hi> Devell <hi>&amp;</hi> Antichriſt, <hi>&amp; ſends more Soules to Hell then all the wickedneſſe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:154971:16"/>
Impietie, ungodlineſſe in the Kingdome doth beſides, is no true</hi> Worſhip <hi>of God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> but ought to be deteſted and abhorred of all his people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But ſuch is the</hi> Worſhip <hi>of the</hi> Church <hi>of England as worthy Dr.</hi> Baſtwicke <hi>in the third part of his</hi> Letany <hi>doth prove.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ergo. <hi>It is no true</hi> Worſhip, <hi>but ought to be deteſted &amp; ſeparated from by all</hi> Gods <hi>faithfull ones.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus much for the anſwering of your third &amp; fourth Arguments, which you ſay are ſo ſtrong and true, that you ſay you need ſpend no more time in the proofe of them, but indeed you are exceedingly miſtaken, for you have not in the leaſt proved either of them, as I have made it manifeſt. Well now to come to your fift Argument, which is thus framed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If the Church of</hi> Engl. <hi>have the true matter and forme of a true Church then it muſt needs be a true Ch. But the Ch. of</hi> Engl. <hi>hath the matter &amp; forme of a true</hi> Church. Ergo. <hi>It is a true viſible</hi> Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 5. I Anſwer, <hi>if it had the true matter &amp; forme of a true viſible Church, then ti were true indeed, for theſe are both and only eſſentiall to the being of a true Ch. but I ſay, you want them both:</hi> But you for to prove it ſay, that the <hi>matter of a true Ch. is a company of men and that you have:</hi> and you ſay the Forme is <hi>a profeſſion of true Religion:</hi> truly you bewray the blindnes and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of a man whſe braines and underſtanding is infatuated and made drunke with the ſpirituall cup of fornication of the ſcarlat whore, not in the leaſt underſtanding what you ſay and affirme: yet to anſwer your Arg. though I grant, <hi>that where true matter and true forme is there is a true Church,</hi> yet I ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely deny that you have either true matter or true forme, which you ſay <hi>you thinke none will deny;</hi> ſo that the begging of things, and takeing that for granted which I deny, and which you are never able to prove, is the beſt ground you have to prove your falſe Arg. true. But now for the matter of a true Ch. you will have it to be <hi>a company of men,</hi> making no diſtinction, but let them be what kind ſoever they will ſerve it ſeemes to be true matter in your ch. whether they be a company of men poſſeſſed with Divels and uncleane ſpirits from whoſe mouth Chriſt will owne no confeſſion, nor ſervice, but abſolutely commands them to hold their peace <hi>and not to take his name in their mouthes to ſpeake of him, Mar.</hi> 1 <hi>s</hi> 25.34. oa whether they be <hi>Inchanters, Sorcerers, or divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi> or wether they be <hi>whoremongers, fornicatorss, Idolaters, adulterers, drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards, ſwearers, blaſpheamers, prophane perſons, lyars, or thoſe that commit the ſin againſt the holy ghoſt, ſo they be but men, let them he what kind of men they will,</hi> you ſay <hi>they are fit matter for a true church;</hi> indeed I confeſſe they are the fitteſt matter for your church that you can have, and your church is made up, and doth conſiſt of all ſuch ſorts &amp; kinds of wicked perſons, which doth evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; and undenyably prove it to be an Antich. Ch. and one of the nationall Citties that is under the government of the Beaſt, for he is ſaid <hi>to compell all as you doe both rich and poor, high &amp; low, bond &amp; free, to become his ſervants &amp; ſubjects and to worſhip him according to his lawes, and whoſoever will not, ſhall not</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:154971:17"/>
live neither in peace nor quietnes. <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.15.16. and this is the practice of your Church daily and hourly: for the moſt unfitteſt matter for your Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches are <hi>the Conſciencious Saints that deſire to glorifie God as well in their Bodys as in their S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ules, and to walke unblameably in all his waies,</hi> and if there be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch among you, they are caſt out of your <hi>Synagogues</hi> by you and prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted either to buy or ſell with you though ſuch as theſe alone be the only true and fit matter for the viſible Church or Kingdome of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt. Eſay.</hi> 35.10. &amp; 51.11. <hi>Jer.</hi> 4.5. <hi>Act.</hi> 1.14.15. &amp; 2.41.47. &amp; 11.21.23. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.7. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.2. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.14. For all uncleane, wicked and ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſons of what ſort ſoever, are no fit matter to become members of <hi>Chriſts</hi> holy City, new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> which is ſaid to come downe from Heaven, or viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Church, for all ſuch ſhould and ought to be kept out from thence. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.40. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.13. &amp; 6.9.10. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.27. &amp; 22.15.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond place you ſay the proffeſſion of true Religion is the forme of a true Church, &amp; this you in <hi>England</hi> doe and have, and therefore are a true Church. For anſwer to which I ſay, <hi>that I have already in the foregoing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe fully proved, that your Religion is not a true Religion but a falſe, ſeing you worſhip and ſerve God, not accoding to his Lawes and commands, but with, and according to your owne deviſes and Inventions, but yet I doe confeſſe that yee doe profeſſe (like the Samaritane) the worſhip of the true God, but for all that (with them) you ſerve your Idols, therefore by your owne grounds you have not the forme of a true Church, wherefore by the ſame Ground it followes that you are not a true Church.</hi> But now punctually to anſwer your Argument, I affirme that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> forme of a true Church is <hi>for a company of beleevers who are waſhed in the bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od of</hi> Chriſt <hi>by a free and voluntary Conſent or willingneſſe to enter into that heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and holy</hi> State, City or Kingdome, which in the word of God is plentiuflly deſcribed, <hi>and by the power of</hi> Chriſt <hi>to become a conſtituted or</hi> Polytique <hi>Body or</hi> Corporation, <hi>or an incloſed or fenced</hi> Garden or Vinyard, and then by vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of their combination uniting &amp; joyning themſelves together each to other &amp; ſo unto the Lord, promiſing to walk in all his waies &amp; to yeild obedience to all his Lawes &amp; commands, as he requires they ſhould. <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6 17.18. they become a true viſible Church of Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.9.10.11. 2 <hi>King.</hi> 11.17. 2 <hi>Cron.</hi> 15.12. <hi>Nehe.</hi> 10.29. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110. 3. <hi>Jer.</hi> 50.4.5. <hi>Act.</hi> 23.24 &amp; ſo hath power from Chriſt her head, to caſt out offenders. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. to chuſe elect &amp; ordaine her own <hi>Officers Act.</hi> 6.3.5. &amp; 14.23. <hi>&amp; they ordained them Elders in every</hi> Church <hi>by Election.</hi> as the <hi>Originall</hi> and <hi>Beza's</hi> Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with others, read it (though the word, Election, by the <hi>Biſhops</hi> fraud and Pollicy, be left out in our laſt <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tranſlation) and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive in beleevers. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.7.8. and to keepe out wicked perſons <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.27. and 22.15. and to reprove and admoniſh her owne <hi>Officers</hi> Biſhops or Overſeers <hi>Col.</hi> 4.17. or doe her ſelfe any ſprituall good, or
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:154971:17"/>
exclude from herſelfe any evill ſhee feares, or is like to come upon her without the helpe or aſſiſtance of any either <hi>church</hi> or <hi>officers</hi> beſides her ſelfe, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.2.3. <hi>ch.</hi> but the Ch. of <hi>Eng.</hi> neither hath, or ever had this forme in the leaſt, as I have fully manifeſted elſewhere: as alſo you may read in a litle Booke lately printed called the <hi>Three Eſtates,</hi> that is to ſay, the <hi>Civill State,</hi> the rrue <hi>Eccleſiaſticall Sate,</hi> and the <hi>Falſe Ecclſiaſticall State,</hi> and alſo you want the <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the true Religion,</hi> and therefore your Ch. is no true Ch. of Chriſt, for it is vnited by profeſſion &amp; ſubjection to the Pope of <hi>Lambeth,</hi> who is ſubſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute to the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> whome <hi>Maſon</hi> in his <hi>Epiſtle Dedicatory</hi> before his Booke of Ordination of Biſhops, Preiſts and Deacons, cals the Head and cheife over the Ch. of Engl. for they in their publike <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>High Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion</hi> at the <hi>cenſure</hi> of that noble and worthy Dr. <hi>Baſtwicke</hi> have renounced the King as <hi>Head</hi> thereof, and have placed it upon the Biſhops of Canterbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, as you may read at large in the 10. and 11. <hi>p.</hi> of his Anſwer to ſir <hi>John Bankes,</hi> if Canterbury be her Head, as <hi>Maſon</hi> and others affirme, then ſure I am, that Chriſt is none of her head, for his body is no monſter, to have two heads Therefore the Church of England is a whoriſh and Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Church, and none of Chriſts, having nothing to doe with Jeſus Chriſt. nor any of his Lawes, Worſhip, Offices, Ordinances or Adminiſtrations; but in the next place you bring an Argument to prove the Religion in the Church of England to be true, and you thus lay it downe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That Religion which will lead men on into the true way of ſalvation, that muſt needs be the true Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But the Religion which we profeſſe leads into the true way of ſalvation, for men to looke for ſalvation in Gods free mercy in Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore (ſay you) your Argument muſt needs be true.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer that if it were granted (which in the leaſt I doe not) that your Religion is true, yet this alone were not ſufficient to prove your Church true. But I abſolutely deny your Argument, and affirme that your Religion neither is the true Religion, nor that it leads men the true way to ſalvation, for I have already proved it to be a falſe Religion, and that it leads men the true way to Rebellion againſt God, and his Son Jeſus Chriſt. But you will ſay how comes it to paſſe that ſome are ſaved, which profeſſe our Religion, which you affirme to be falſe? I anſwer in <hi>Moſes</hi> words, <hi>hidden things belongs to God, but revealed things to us and our Children, Devt.</hi> 29.29. but yet when I ſeriouſly conſider of it, and with a deliberate eye looke into the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the revealed will of God, it makes me thinke, ſay, and cry out with <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 11.33. <hi>O the depthes of the riches both of the wiſedome and knowledge of God, how unſpeakeable are his judgments, and his wayes paſt finding out,</hi> who can ſave his People, thoſe <hi>elect ones,</hi> even in the boſome of Antichriſt his curſed Kingdome of darkneſſe, contrary to all grounded rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:154971:18"/>
that the wit of man is able to give or render from his revealed will, but only muſt ſay, it is alone his meer mercy, and gratious, and omnipotent plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ſo to doe, who is tyed to no meanes, place or perſon, but can worke, and bring to paſſe his owne ends, and purpoſes without meanes, yea and beyond all outward meanes, 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 19.10.17. <hi>Ezec.</hi> 57. for the <hi>holy one of Iſrael</hi> is not limited. But to prove this Argument you lay downe an other after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. <hi>If men profeſſing the ſame way to ſalvation that we doe, have lived and dyed in the profeſſion of it, and been ſaved, then is the Religion and way to ſalvation that we profeſſe a true Religion and way to ſalvation. But men that profeſſe our Religion have been ſaved.</hi> Ergo <hi>it is true.</hi> what childiſh reaſoning is here to beg things after this manner, and to judge the cauſe by the effect contrary to the whole currant of the Scripture, for it doth largly ſhew, that a bad and wicked cauſe or action may produce and bring forth a good and glorious effect and this is juſt as they ſaid in <hi>Pauls</hi> time, <hi>let us doe evill that good may come of it,</hi> but ſaith he, ſuch mens damnation is juſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.8. and if you have read the Scripture, (which it appeares you have not very often) you may know, that the <hi>Midwives,</hi> and <hi>Harlot Rahabs lying</hi> ſaved the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> children, and the <hi>Spies</hi> lives, <hi>Exod.</hi> 1. <hi>Joſh.</hi> 2. for which act of mercy they are commended in the Word of God, and alſo it produced good effects to them, for the Lord cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the <hi>Midwives</hi> to proſper, and ſaved <hi>Rahab</hi> alive, yet for all this they ſinned in lying, and doe you not know, that the Word of God ſaith wee muſt <hi>not doe the leaſt evill that the greateſt good may come of it:</hi> but yet by your reaſoning a man may, which to affirme is the height of wickednes, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety, and alſo by your reaſoning a man may defend and juſtifie all the ſinnes and ſayings of Gods people, and others recorded in the Booke of God, out of which that God that is able to bring light out of darkenes, and good out of evill, hath brought much glory to himſelfe, as out of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> hard hearted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and blood thirſty cruelty that he exerciſed upon Gods people, it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced good to them, by working their deliverance, and glory to God, by manifeſting his power and goodnes, yet for all this <hi>Pharaohs</hi> ſin was never the leſſe. And alſo according to your reaſoning <hi>Judas</hi> his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon might be excuſed, for that ſin of his brought a world of glory unto God, and ſalvation and eternall glory to his elect and choſen ones; yet though his betraying of Chriſt did produce ſuch a good and glorious effect it did nothing at all excuſe his ſin.</p>
            <p>Againe your Arg. is nothing to the purpoſe to prove that which you have undertaken, for we are not reaſoning of the way and meanes of ſalvation, which is only and alone by faith in the Lord Chriſt, which is poſſible may be had in a falſe Ch. yea alſo in no Ch. but the thing we are about is to prove &amp; ſee whether the Ch. of Eng. be a true Ch. of Chriſt, or a falſe Ch. of <hi>Antichr.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But yet more fully to Anſwer your Argument what though it
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:154971:18"/>
be confeſſed that many of God <hi>Elect</hi> have been ſaved, that have profeſſed your falſe and Antichr. Rel. it will not therefore follow, that your Religion is a true Religion, nor your church a true church, becauſe ſome have been ſaved, that have profeſſed it: I hope you will not ſo conclude, which if you doe, then I ſay by your owne grounds, <hi>that the chruch of Rome is a true church, the Religion there a true Religion,</hi> for many therein have loſt their lives for the maintaining of ſome truths, which have yet adheared to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> &amp; of many of their eternall happines, as good grounds may be given as the moſt of the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs of the ch. of <hi>Eng.</hi> yea, and I verily beleive, that God hath had, and ſtill hath a people there which belongs to his <hi>Election of grace,</hi> which both hath and will ſave, and ſo by your owne grounds their church and Religion are both true, becauſe it is poſſible that ſome that profeſſe have been and ſtill may be ſaved But if you will maintaine this, then you contradict your owne writers, which have plentifully proved the Religion in <hi>Rome</hi> and the church thereof, to be falſe, and yet have granted that ſome have been ſaved there, &amp; therefore for you to goe about to prove rhe church of <hi>Engl.</hi> true, and the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip therein true, becauſe ſome of the members thereof that have profeſſed the Religion therin have been ſaved, is an erronious &amp; unſound ground, for by this ground it will follow, that the <hi>Croſſe</hi> upon which the Theife was han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged was a true church, for there he had ſalvation &amp; the apprehenſion of Gods love, &amp; his aſſurance of his enterance into the Kingdome of glory, as fully as ever any in the ch. of <hi>En.</hi> had; and alſo it will follow, that the <hi>Chariot</hi> in which the <hi>Eunuch</hi> rode, <hi>Acts</hi> 8. was a true ch. for there he came to the knowledg of his ſalvation &amp; the apprehenſion of the true love of God in Chriſt; alſo you know God by his almighty power ſaved <hi>Daniel &amp; the three children</hi> alive even in the <hi>Lyons den,</hi> and in the hot burning furnace, and becauſe <hi>God</hi> by his power did this, ſhall I therefore goe caſt my falſe into the fire, and among the Lyons, &amp; ſay, they have no power to burne me, or kill me, but I am ſafe enough becauſe <hi>God</hi> preſerved <hi>Daniel,</hi> and the <hi>three children</hi> alive in the like condition: every wiſe man would conclude ſurely I were out of my wits: So you ſee how er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronious, rotten, inſufficient &amp; unſound all your grounds &amp; arguments are in the lying downe of which you run with your deceitfull <hi>Logike, like a blind horſe in a mill, about, &amp; about, and ſtill come to the ſame place, where you begun, never in the leaſt prove any thing you ſay by the authority of the word of God, nor yet by any grounded reaſon, but ruly your falſe affirmations, for the wind that comes out of you. mouth, is ſo weak and feeble, that it will ſcarce blow away a ſtraw if it lie in your way</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And then in the laſt place, you bring an Arg. in the necke of this, being of the ſame nature with the former, and it is this. <hi>That becauſe Latimer, Hooper &amp; Bradford, with many others were martyrs in your ch. and were ſaved ss<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> by the judgment of charity (not infalibly) wee may judge were ſaved, and knew the corruptions of your church, and yet did not ſeparate away</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:154971:19"/>
from it, therefore it is a true Church, and need not be ſeparated from, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing men may be ſaved in it. Truly I muſt confeſſe unto you, I am almoſt weary with anſwering your paultery, old, rotten, mouldy ſtuffe, and you are ſuch a novice in the miſteries of God and godlyneſſe, and the Kingdome of his Son Jeſus Chriſt, not underſtanding what you ſay, or affirme, nor bow to prove an Argument, that I am almoſt loath any more to contend with you in regard the victory in overcomeing you will be ſo poore and meane, and your wares are ſuch paltery, and peplary commodities, that I am even tyred with lookeing upon them and turning them over: but yet for all this I will a litle reply to this your laſt Argument, but I hope you do not hold that <hi>maxime</hi> in the Church of <hi>Rome, extra eccleſia nulla ſalus,</hi> that is, out of the Church no ſalvation, if you doe, it is moſt erronious, for I have proved it, and the whole New Teſtament doth declare it, that it is poſſible for a man to be ſaved, though he be a member of no viſible Church; yea and that ſome that are joyned to a falſe Church may be ſaved, but yet if they may be ſo, it is no ground for their ſtaying, or abiding there, for God cals, and commands all his people to be ſeparated from the World, and all falſe churches, 2 Cor. 6.16.17.18. Rev. 18.4. but it ſeemes by your reaſoning, you hold that if a man get ſalvation, and get to heaven, and ſo get his own ends ſerved, let Gods glory goe a begging, and lye at the ſtake a bleeding for all you, but truly ſuch a ſervant deſerves no wages, but rather puniſhent; for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las man this is but ſelfe ſeeking at the beſt, in which a man can have no ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall comfort, and joy: But God would have his people to joy and rejoyc in walking in his wayes, and ſing and be merry, and be of a chearefull counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, as it doth become the heires of the Crowne of glory, and he would have them not only as it were creep into Heaven, but to ſtrive and labour to have an abundant enterane thereinto, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 19.10.11. but by your reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning you would have them never be merry, joyfull, nor chearfull (for in falſe wayes there is no peace nor comfort, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 59 8 9.11. <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.2.) but live like forlorne men deſtitute of all comfort, hanging downe their heads like bulruſhes, and ſo diſhonour their God and their Chriſt in the eyes of the men of the world, who will glory and triumph over them, as though there were not that ſweetnes, beautifulnes, amiablenes, fulnes, ſatisfaction and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tednes in the enjoying of God in his Son Chriſt, that might make them walke with merry counterances, chearfull hearts and reioycing ſoules, as it becomes the Sons and heires of the King of glory, diſdaining, contemning, and lightly eſteeming the baſe and empty moth eaten contents of this preſent world, and to have their affections crucified to it, and it to them, and though they be in the world, yet to walke as thoſe whoſe converſation is already in Heaven, longing and deſiring to be diſſolved to be with Chriſt which is beſt of all: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way man, Chriſt hath no need of ſuch unſerviceable ſelfe ſeeking ſervants as you
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:154971:19"/>
               <hi>on are, to weare his glorious and rich Livery, and let me tell you, God never ſent his ſonne Chriſt to ſave us for that end to live at eaſe, and delight, as we lift, or in the faſhion of the World: but that we ſhould glorifie him in being unlike to the World in our lives and converſation by an unblameable walking in all his wayes, labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and endeavouring to yeild obedience to all his Lawes and commaunds, not ſuffering our hearts to be poſſeſſed with baſe feares of the world, nor be in love with the things thereof, but that wee ſhould hold forth the profeſſion of the purity of his truth and Goſpell without feare before the eyes of the world, and though wee ſuffer perſecution, affliction and tribulation for it, that wee ſhould joy and rejoce in it and eſteem it our Crown and happines that the Lord counts us worthy to ſuffer for, his ſake:</hi> And truly let me tell you, he that ſeekes but his own ends, and ſo that he could be but ſaved cares for no more, not regarding or takeing thought what becomes of Gods glory, honour and praiſe, it is an evident and demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrable ſigne, that that man doth not belong to God, nor never ſhall be heire of glory, <hi>John</hi> 14.23.24. <hi>&amp;</hi> 25.8.14. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.8.10. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2.9. <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.11. <hi>&amp;</hi> 14.4.</p>
            <p>And what if <hi>Latimer,</hi> and the reſt of the martyrs had communion with the Church of England, is that a ſufficient ground, that therefore wee muſt not ſeparate away from it,? I hope not, for what if God winked at their blindnes, darkenes, and ignorance, yet now let me ſay with Paul, <hi>that in truth he will have all his people to come to the knowledge of his truth and wayes, Acts</hi> 17.20. becauſe <hi>he hath appoynted a day, wherein he will ſhortly judge that great ſcarlet whore of</hi> Rome, <hi>and all her nationall churches, cityes, or daughters that depend vpon her, one of which</hi> England <hi>is; and woe to that man at that day, that is found within her territories, or the Paile of her great catholike church, or the walls of her great wide and farre ſpread ſpirituall citty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alas man there is a great deale of difference betwixt King <hi>Edwards</hi> and Queen <hi>Maryes</hi> times, and ours now; the martyrs and people of God were then but newly enlightned, to ſee the blake and ſpirituall darke Kingdome of Satan, and Antichriſt, in which they were brought up, the darkeneſſe whereof was ſo great, the Sun and the Aire was both clouded, <hi>Rev.</hi> 9 2. and the bright, ſhining light of the old and new Teſtament ſhut vp in much obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to what it is now, and they did but ſee the abominable wickednes of his kingdome a farre of, like the man in the Goſpell, whoſe eyes Chriſt opened, who at his firſt looking up, did ſee men walking a farre off like trees, even ſo they ſaw but the truthes a farre off, which made them rejoyce at a little Reformation, and highly to eſteeme of thoſe things in the worſhip and ſervice of God, that now are made manifeſt by the light of truth before the open Sun, to be no fitter for Gods worſhip and Service then kennell dirte, being meer Idols, and thoſe Idolaters that communicate with them, and though they rejoyced at a little Reformation of Antichriſts errours; but now
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:154971:20"/>
it is made manifeſt that no <hi>Reformation</hi> of his <hi>Kingdome</hi> will ſerve the turne, but it muſt be now annihilated and nullified before the viſible <hi>Kingdome</hi> of Chriſt can <hi>flouriſh,</hi> and <hi>become the praiſe of the whole Earth,</hi> and you know and confeſſe they would have no <hi>Communion</hi> with the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> from which they thought they had ſeperated, neither with that abominable <hi>Idoll</hi> the <hi>Maſſe</hi> which you confeſſe they counted deteſtable, though they had <hi>communion</hi> with the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> and the <hi>Service-Booke,</hi> but now the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> is proved againe and againe by hundreds of the <hi>Seperation,</hi> and others in their diſputes, Sermons and writings, to be as <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> and the <hi>Service Booke</hi> to be as deteſtable as the <hi>Idol</hi> of the <hi>Maſſe,</hi> being even one and the ſame with it, ſaving that it is in <hi>Latine</hi> and this in <hi>Engliſh</hi> (as No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Dr. <hi>Baſtwicke</hi> hath proved) <hi>And what though the abomination and fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that great Red WHOORE of Rome, in</hi> King Edwards <hi>time was not ſo ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly laid open, but that the Martyrs and choſen people of God did then commit ſome ſpirituall Fornication with her, muſt we therefore doe the like? no, God forbid! for the</hi> Lambe <hi>that ſtandeth upon mount</hi> Syon <hi>with an Hundred fourty and four Thow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand of his Elect and choſen ones having his Fathers name written in their Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads hath proclaimed and made it manifeſt, that</hi> Babilon <hi>or ſpiritaall</hi> Rome <hi>is now fallen and is become the habitation of Divells, and tho hold of every ſoul ſpirit and the Cage of every uncleane and hatefull, Bird: with whom Gods people now at no hand are not to be mixed in ſpirituall Society or Communion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what though the everlaſting <hi>Goſpell</hi> then was not ſo fully preached and revealed as now it is, ſo that Gods people then were exceeding ignorant of it, and by their blindneſſe thought they thought they had ſeperated away from the <hi>Beaſts</hi> Kingdome, yet were they in it, and did worſhip him, muſt it then follow that we muſt doe ſo too? no: for now the great City <hi>Rome</hi> is, much more fallen and deſcovered then it was: and now a third <hi>Angell</hi> hath proclaimed it with a lowd voyce having his Commiſſion from God ſo to doe <hi>that ſeing now the Booke is opened, and the trueth of the everlaſting Goſpell is prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and Light is now brought into the world: ſo that now if after all this a man worſhip the</hi> Beaſt <hi>and his</hi> Image, <hi>or receive in his right hand or in his forhead his marke, the ſame ſhall drink of the wine of the wrath of God, which is powred out without mixture into the</hi> Cup <hi>of his</hi> Indignation, <hi>and he ſhall be tormented with Fire and Brimſtone in the preſence of the</hi> Angells, <hi>and in the preſence of the</hi> Lambe, <hi>and the ſmoke of their Torment aſcended up for ever and ever, and they have no reſt day nor night that worſhip the</hi> Beaſt <hi>or his</hi> Image, <hi>or receive the marke of his Name. Rev.</hi> 14.8.9.10.11. Wherefore ſaith the Spirit of God, <hi>Came out of her any people, that ye be not partakers of her ſinnes,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:154971:20"/>
and that yee receive not of her plagues,</hi> chap. 18.5. here is the expreſſe command of God himſelfe to all his choſen and elect ones to ſeparate away from all An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian Aſſemblies, and not in the leaſt to partake with them in any of their worſhip, ordinances, or adminiſtrations, which precept if any of them refuſe to obey, let them know, that God will plague them, and though for his Covenant ſake, he ſave their ſoules, yet it will be through much difficulty, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companed with many an heavy and ſad heart, and many a bitter uncomfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Croſſe. Therefore let all Gods people that yet are in her, or in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of the Church of England, her daughter, as they love their own inward peace, and ſpirituall joy, and looke that their ſoules ſhould proſper and flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh with grace and Godlines looke to it, and withdraw their ſpirituall obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and ſubjection from all Antichriſts Lawes and worſhip, and now joyne themſelves as fellow Cttizens of the City of God, to worſhip and ſerue him in <hi>mount Syon</hi> the beauty of holyneſſe, and there only to yeild all ſpirituall obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to Chriſts ſpirituall Lawes and Scepter.</p>
            <p>Now my <hi>Oppoſite,</hi> I have fully by the authority of the ſacred and pure word of God, particularly anſwered your trifling, childiſh and frothy arguments, and proved againſt you and them, that the <hi>church, miniſtery and worſhip in</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>is all of them Antichriſtian, from which all Gods people are bound in conſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, ind in paine of undergoing the Lords high diſpleaſure hnd indignation, and heing portakers of his fearfull and dreadfull plagues, to ſeparate away from it, and to have no communion with it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore to you my <hi>Oppoſer</hi> I ſay with the <hi>Prophet</hi> to backſtyding <hi>Iſrael, I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God be God follow him, or if Baall</hi> or Antichriſt or Rome <hi>he God then fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo much for the Anſwering of your erronious Arguments.</p>
            <p>BUt now you will, it may be ſay, if ſalvation as you have confeſſed and proved may be had in a falſe Ch. yea in no Gh. then wherefore doe you enter into, and become a member of a true Church? My Anſw. to this is, in the firſt place <hi>negatively:</hi> I doe not enter thereinto for to be ſaved thereby, or for to ſeeke for Jeſus Chriſt, as though I wanted either, for I have both Chriſt and ſalvation, as all thoſe ought to have, that become <hi>fellow citzens</hi> of the City of God, as I have before largely proved, neither doe I enter into into it to live ſecurely and careleſly in ſin &amp; pleaſure, looſenes of life and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation; no, none ſuch are fit to be there, and if any ſuch creepe in thither, us it is poſſible they may, they ought to be caſt out from them, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.13. But affirmatively in the ſecond place I anſwer, That I enter into it, Firſt in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to Gods command, <hi>Eſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 26.20. who hath commanded and enjoyned me, and all his faithfull people to become Citizens of his City, and members of his viſible church, there to worſhip him <hi>Syon, the beauty of holynes,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his owne Lawes and appoyntment. Againe I enter into a true Church
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:154971:21"/>
eſtate, <hi>to honour and glorifie my God, who hath paſſed by ſo many thouſands as he hath done, and left them in their ſins, and yet hath choſen me freely before the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the world was laid; out of the riches and abundance of his grace, and through and for his Son Chriſt my Saviours ſake, by whoſe blood my ſoule is waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and cleanſed from all my ſins and pollutions, and preſented ſpoiles and blameles before his and my heavenly father, by which I am made fit, being an beir of glory, to partake with him in eternall glory in the never ending Kingdome of glory, with unſpeakable grace, mercy, and favour,</hi> ties and binds me to walke uprightly and is blameable without feare or ſelfe reſpects in all his wayes and commaunds, and with all my ſtrength and might to ſet forth his praſie, and to honour and glorifie his great and holy name, which is done by my publike and open pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing of the purity of his truth, and walking inoffenſibly and unreproveable in all his pathes, endeavouring to the utmoſt of my power, being aſſiſted with his renuing ſpirit, (who is the worker of all my workes in me and for me) to yeild willing and cheerfull obedience to all his Lawes &amp; commaunds, by the doing of which, light doth ſhine ſo before men, that they may ſee my good workes, and ſo glorifie my father which is in heaven. Alſo by this I become a <hi>witneſſe bearer</hi> againſt the world, leaving them without the leaſt excuſe before God in the day of their great accon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt, in that I eſteem the enjoying of God in his Chriſt above all earthly favours &amp; riches, the ſweetnes of which makes me with wilingnes and cheerfulnes freely &amp; willingly to part with all worldly treaſures, delights, &amp; pleaſures aed with rejoyceing &amp; glorying to ſuffer perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, tribulation, and all ſorte of affliction for the enjoying of him, and yet though I profeſſe the truth of God amongſt the men of the world, and doe ſo highly prize it, and eſteem it worthy the looſing of my life for it, yet they nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doe nor will imbrace it, has deſpiſe and reject it, which makes their ſin inexouſable. Alſo I enter into a true church eſtate, as into a ſpeaciall place of ſhelter, and reſume, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 4.5.6. where God in an eſpeaciall manner hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to be a ſhielder &amp; defender of me from harmes and dangers which when I ſee are, I may preſſe him with the makeing good of his promiſe, who in eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall manner hath promiſed to be an hiding place to his people walking here in his wayes; whereas though I be his, yet if I walke in falſe wayes, and have communion with falſe Aſſemblyes, which it is poſſible for Gods owne people to doe, then am I without all promiſe of protection, peace and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort; for God is terrible and dreadfull out of his holy place, or in falſe wayes or in wayes of our owne invention we ſhall neither find nor know prace, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 29.13. &amp; 50.10. &amp; 59.8.10.11. &amp; he hath threatned to curſe thoſe bleſſings that are got therein, <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.2. for <hi>the vine thereof is as the vine af Sodom, &amp; of the feilds of Gomorah, their grapes are grapos of gall, and their cluſters are bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, their wine is the poyſon of Draggans, and the cruell venome of Aſpes, Deut</hi> 32.32.33. but his viſible Ch. (or Kingdom) is his City walled, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21 which he will ſave &amp; protect his vineyard fenced, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 5. which he will keep
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:154971:21"/>
               <hi>Eſa.</hi> 27.3. his Garden encloſed, which he will preſerve; his Spring ſhut up, which he will de end; his fountaine ſealed, which he will not ſuffer to be be broaken open, <hi>Can.</hi> 4.2. his body pelitique, over which he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s Head, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.22. and therefore bearing a a tender love to the members thereof, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.23.25.30. he will not ſuffer them to be wronged, but will defend them from their enemies, and keep them in the midſt of all afflictions, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 43.1.2. &amp; 41.10.11.14. &amp; 54.17. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.5.6. Alſo I enter into a true Ch. eſtate, there to find Gods eſpeaciall preſence, which he hath promiſed therein <hi>Pſal.</hi> 0.11. &amp; 4.6.4.5.68.16. <hi>Jer.</hi> 8.3. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.3.22.23. and that I might grow &amp; increaſe in grace which he hath promiſed there, <hi>Pſ:</hi> 132.13.14.15.16. &amp; 133.3. <hi>Jer.</hi> 8. for he hath ſaid he will water it every moment <hi>Eſa.</hi> 27.3. that ſo his people may become fruitfull and grow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d like tall <hi>Cedars</hi> in <hi>Lebanon.</hi> Laſtly, I enter into it, that I might draw more to my God, and gaine more and more ſpirituall fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and communion with him, and that I might make my election &amp; ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſure, that ſo an enterance abundantly may be adminiſtred unto me, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the everlaſting Kingdome of our Lord &amp; Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, 9 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10.11. and that ſo I may walke comfortably, irejoyceingly &amp; cheerfully, as it doth become one vnited to the Lord of glory, in the profeſſing of whom alone ſo much riches, treaſure, comfort, rejoyceing and unſpeakeable joy is to be found &amp; had, that a beleiver may ſpend largely &amp; plentifully all his dayes upon and live like a King, and be never able to exhauſt it. And thoſe are my rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons amongſt many others. Wherfore though God hath manfeſted his love and kindnes unto me in his ſon, yet I deſire according to my duty to enter into a viſible Church, as a viſible chriſtian, there publikely in the eyes of his people to worſhip and ſerve hem only according to his owne Lawes, without any mans inventions whatſoever.</p>
            <p>But now to ſay a litle to that, which followeth your Arguments, and ſo I will conclude. You deſire to let your Freind know, <hi>there have been known wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men in a true Ch. and therefore though in the Ch. of</hi> Eng. <hi>there be all ſorts of wicked men, yet Gods people may have communion with them, becauſe there were wicked men in the Ch. of the Jewes, and the Corinthes:</hi> And this is that you labour to prove, let me tell you, <hi>you might have ſaved your ſelfe a great deale of paines, for the</hi> Separation <hi>de confeſſi &amp; acknowledg, that there hath been wicked men, and alſo corruptions in a true Ch.</hi> and that ſtill may ſo fall out, that yet in may be ſo, and yet not the eſſence of it deſtroyed: but what get you by this? for this will not ſerve turne, to warrant communion with the Ch. of <hi>Eng.</hi> in regard I groundedly &amp; abſolutely deny, that either the Ch. of <hi>Eng.</hi> is or ever was a true Ch. and till you have proved it true, all the paines that you have taken in proving that <hi>it is poſſible for corruptions and wicked livers to be in a true Ch.</hi> is ſpent in vaine and to no purpoſe, and I am confident, that you nor none elſe will ever be able to prove the Ch. of <hi>Eng.</hi> true, nor any other Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall Ch. for Jeſus Chriſt by his death did aboliſh the National Church of the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:154971:22"/>
Jewes, with all there Lawes, rites and Ceremonies thereof, and in the new Teſtament did never inſtitute no nationall Ch. nor left no Lawe, nor Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers for the governing thereof,, but the Church that he inſtituted, are free and indedendant bodies, or Congregations depending upon none but only upon Chriſt their Head: Therefore, nationall Churches under the Goſpell are of Antichriſts, <hi>that man of ſins</hi> inſtitution and ordaining, who only hath ordained Lawes and officers of his owne for the governing of them, as I have ſufficiently proved at large in my foreſaid Anſwer to W. G. and but put the eaſe, the Ch. of <hi>Eng.</hi> had been a true Ch. as it never was, yet thoſe abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable corruptions, and moſt deteſtable, groſſe, open, notoriovs wickednes and prophanes, would have utterly deſtroyed long ere this her Eſſence and Being, and have made her utterly to have forfeited her Charter, and have ceaſed to a true Ch. for if God threatned to unchurch the Ch. of <hi>Epheſus, Rev.</hi> 2. and to take his heavenly ſtate, Charter, and <hi>Candleſticke</hi> frow her, for but <hi>forſake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her firſt Love;</hi> and the Gh. of <hi>Pergamus</hi> for having ſome in her that <hi>taught the Doctrin of Balam;</hi> and the Ch. of <hi>Thiatira</hi> for ſuffering <hi>Jeſabels doctrine</hi> to preached amonſt them: doe you think that he would haue ſpared the Ch. of <hi>Eng.</hi> to this day, who for many hundred yeares, even ever ſince her firſt conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, take her at her beſt, hath been ten times worſe then all theſe, in which all manner of falſe doctrines have been manifeſtly maintained and preached, and all kind of prophanes &amp; wickednes by her nembers practiced &amp; perpetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Therefore for you, or any other to ſay, and affirme, that this monſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ugly, botched and skabbed body, is Chriſts true Spouſe, is diſhonourable to his bleſſed Being and Mediatorſhip, who gave himſelfe for his Ch., that he might ſanctifie and cleanſe it with the waſhing of water by the Word, &amp; that he might, preſerve it to himſelf a glorious Ch. not having ſpot, or wrinkle, or any ſuch thing; but that it ſhould be holy, and without blemiſh, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.26.27. for the name of this City, is the Lord is there, <hi>Ezr.</hi> 48.15. all the true In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of which, are to be righteous as the ſervants and elect ones of the Lord, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 60.21. &amp; 65.2. but in the Ch. of Engl. he that is moſt acute in teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing falſe doctrine, and ſetting up Antichriſts wicked Kingdom, climbes to the higheſt preferment and Church dignity, as they call it, witnes, the prophane ignorant, ſottiſh, athieſticall Biſhops, who are ſo voyde of underſtanding in the miſteries of God and godlines, that they dare not publikely diſpute with the yongueſt boy, that doth oppoſe them, though they have been challeng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to it. Alſo he that commits the moſt widkednes and ungodlynes, is the beſt loved and reſpected, and thoſe that labour to oppoſe falſe doctrine and walke more holyer then others, are the moſt hated, deſpiſed and reejcted, and this even in the boſome of your Church, even by the Pillars and corner ſtones thereof, witnes thoſe late, bloody, barbarous, and tyrannicall cutting of mens eares at the Pillory, and whipping others at the Cart, that even for conſcience ſake: therefore doe you thinke, or have you any ground to imagine
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:154971:22"/>
that if ever your Ch. had been true, but that theſe tranſcendant, exceeding groſſe &amp; vile corruptions, would not have nullified deſtroy'd and annihilated her, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e made Chriſt long ere now, to have given her a <hi>Byll of Divorce,</hi> as he did to <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>keſlyding Iſrael,</hi> and to have taken her Charter from her, as he hath done from all thoſe famous, flouriſhing &amp; renouned Churches recorded in the New Teſtament. It is true, The Ch. of the Jewes had groſſe &amp; mighty cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions in her, which was the height of her ſin, for which God ſeverly plagud and puniſhed her many times: And what if ſhe had ſuch things in her, that will not in the leaſt defend the mighty corruptions in your Ch. ſeeing as I have proved, it never was a true Ch. no nor never ſo long as ſhe ſtands in that falfe Antichriſtian, Nationall ſtate as ſhe doth; but as for the Ch. of the Jewes, it was a true Ch. unto whom God truly gave his Lawes &amp; Ordinances, in the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation &amp; keeping of which, ſhe might have continued lovely, amiable, and beautifull in his eyes, but yours hath not her Power, Lawes and Ordinances from God, but from the Divell &amp; Antich. <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.2.4. It is true, it was the ſin of the Jewes to commit ſuch groſſe evils, as they did, and to ſuffer the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders amongſt them to goe unpuniſhed, contrary to their wholeſome Lawes &amp; Gods own commaund, who had ordained &amp; commanded them, that the ſoule that committed ſuch &amp; ſuch evils, ſhould be out off, &amp; deſtroyed from amongſt the people (as you may largely read in the 4. laſt Bookes of <hi>Moſes</hi>) becauſe the Land as well as the people was an holy Land by virtue of Gods inſtitution of it, and ſetting it a part for himſelfe, as well as the people; and therefore he would have had haynous tranſgreſſours to be deſtroyed, or killed, leaſt the Land ſhould be polluted &amp; deſiled with their wickednes, as he himſelfe ſpeakes, now becauſe they would not obſerve the Lawes &amp; Ordinances that he had given them, though he ſuffered their manners long, and bare much with their ſin, in that he fatherly chaſtiſed and corrected them againe &amp; againe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he utterly deſtroyed them, and anhialated their nationall Ch. that ſo they might be left without excuſe, but ſeeing no Reformatton after ſo many cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections could not be had, but their prophanations and groſſe abominations were ſo great and continued in, it cauſed him at the laſt utterly to renounce them, and for ever put an end unto their nationall C. and Ceremoniall Law, which was done at the death of Chriſt, when he ſpake, and ſaid, <hi>it is finiſhed</hi> and now he will never any more returne againe unto them, to become an huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, as he was to the Nation of the Jewes, though yet he hath, as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures declare an elect remnant and company amongſt them, and at the end of their Nationall Church, Jeſus Chriſt <hi>the eternall Son of God</hi> by virtue of that power, which he had received of and from his Father, changed their Lawes &amp; Ordinances, as the Hiſtory of the <hi>Acts of the Apoſtles</hi> with the reſt of the new Teſtament doth fully declare, and he inſtitued no nationall, but particular Churches or Congregations, many of which may be in one Countrey or nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; all of them independant bodyes, depending upon none, but only upon
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:154971:23"/>
               <hi>Chriſt</hi> their head, and withall inſtituted for it ſpirituall matter, the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of which are to be <hi>Beleevers,</hi> as I have already largely proved, <hi>&amp; from them only and alone he will accept Service and homage Eſay.</hi> 43.21. <hi>&amp;</hi> 51.7. <hi>for they alone &amp; no others have true right to take his name in their mouth, &amp; to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare his Statutes &amp; to meddle with his Law, &amp; Teſtimony Pſal.</hi> 50.16. <hi>Prov.</hi> 15:8.9. <hi>&amp;</hi> 21.27. <hi>Eſay</hi> 8.16. <hi>Mar.</hi> 4.34. <hi>&amp; alſo inſtituted for his Church a ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Worſhip, ſpirituall Lawes, ſpirituall Government ſpirituall Ordinances, ſpirituall Adminiſtrations, which none upon pain of Rebellion againſt</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>the ſonne of God &amp; Wiſedome of his father, are to adde to, or detract from.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, in the ſecond place, it is true, that many of thoſe Churches which Chriſt in his new Teſtament inſtituted, as the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> for one, in proceſſe of time became corrupt, and had groſſe Offenders in her, yet though at the firſt Conſtitution of the Church of <hi>Corinth, Rome</hi> and others did conſiſt of Saints <hi>by calling, and ſanctified</hi> in Chriſt Jeſus <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.1.2. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.22. that is to ſay, <hi>ſuch as by their outward converſation did declare, that they were united by faith to Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> and what though afterward they had corruptions in them, yet that makes nothing at all for you, for firſt, I put you to prove, <hi>that ever your Ch. was true,</hi> which if you cannot doe, to plead that <hi>corruptions may be in a true Church,</hi> will doe you no good, nor ſerve nothing to your purpoſe, nor be no way advantagious to your Ch. which alway even from the firſt day hath been falſe &amp; antichriſtian, and what though <hi>Corinth</hi> had <hi>offenders</hi> in her, did God winke at them, or did <hi>Paul</hi> the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> connive at their wickednes? no, for he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded them to caſt out the <hi>inceſtious perſon,</hi> or give him over to Satan, <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 1. <hi>chp.</hi> 5. as he himſelfe did, <hi>Hymeneus</hi> &amp; <hi>Alexander,</hi> that <hi>ſo they may learne not to blaſpheame,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.20. which <hi>caſting out into the world</hi> under the Goſpell, is as great a ſpirituall puniſhment, as killing of the body was to the Jewes cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall. Alſo he commaunds them, that if any of their members were a <hi>forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catur, or coveteous, or an Idolater, or a railer, or a drunkard, or an extortioner,</hi> that they ſhould avoyde him, and not keep companie with him, <hi>no not ſo much as to eate with him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> ver. 11. But now if this rule ſhould be narrowly obſerved in your church, as it ought to be in all true viſible churches of Jeſus Chriſt, I wonder with whom a man ſhould have any ſpirituall ſociety or communion, ſure I am, not with one amongſt ten thouſand in your Ch. no nor with one at all, it being in every reſpect ſo groſly papiſticall, antichriſtian &amp; idolatrous.</p>
            <p>Againe, as for that place which in the 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. <hi>laſt end</hi> you cite, where he ſaith, <hi>that he was afraid, that he ſhould be troubled among them, not finding them ſuch as he would, and that he ſhould be humbled among them, in bewayling mamy which have ſinned already, and have not repented of their uncleanenes, fornication, and laſciviouſnes, which they had committed,</hi> but if you read the next chap. you ſhall ſee how he threatneth them, and tels them, that <hi>at his comeing againe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, though before he had vſed gentilenes and mildnes, yet now he will not
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:154971:23"/>
ſpare them, but exercize warrantable ſharpne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s and rigour towards them, accoding to that power which the Lord had given unto him to edificati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, and not to deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, ſeing (as he ſaith) he can doe nothing againſt the truth but for the truth,</hi> ſo that you ſe, though there were corruptions amongſt them and groſſe ſinners yet there is no conniving at it, nor no tollerating of it, but ſharp and bitter reproving of it. And as for the reſt of thoſe other Scriptures which you cite I anſwer to them as before, and grant that there was groſſe corruptions in many of the Churches recorded in the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> yet I ſay and affirme, it was their ſin to ſuffer, for which God admoniſhed and threatned them, as you may read in the 2. &amp; 3 <hi>Chap.</hi> of the <hi>Rev.</hi> which became they continued conſtant in their ſin, and would not reforme and amend themſelves as they ought and had power to have done, God hath taken away his <hi>Candleſticke</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> heavenly ſtate from them: <hi>Whoſe examples ſerve for all other</hi> Churches <hi>war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,</hi> for God hath caſt them all off and unchurched them, taking the fo fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of their heavenly <hi>Charter,</hi> as is to be ſeen at this day. Yea alſo the Chur. in and at <hi>Rome it ſelfe, though once the Faith thereof was ſpoken of to the praiſe of the Saints therein throughout the whole World Rom.</hi> 4.8. Yet they alſo are caſt off, and are now no Church of Chriſt, but is become long and many years ſince <hi>the ſeat of Antichriſt the man of ſinne, that ſonne of perdition who oppoſeth and exalteth himſelfe above all that is called God.</hi> 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.3.4. that is to ſay, above all Civill Magiſtrates, yea Emperours kings and Princes, which the Spirit of God in the <hi>Booke of the Pſalmes</hi> calleth Gods. <hi>And is become the Habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Divells and the hold of every fowll ſpirit, and a Cage for every uncleane and hatefull Bird to reſt in, with whom all Nations have been made drunke, and ſtill are, with the wine of the wrath of her ſpirituall Fornication, with whom the Merchants of the Earth are growen rich through the ahoundance of her delicacy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Rev.</hi> 18.2.3. that is to ſay, her <hi>Officers,</hi> which the Spirit of God calleth here, <hi>Merchants,</hi> by virtue of their <hi>Offices,</hi> have got fat and rich benefices, which they call Spirituall Promotions, by which they are mightily ſwelled up with Pride, Venerie and Luxury, but their day is ſhortly a comming, wherein they ſhall cry with weeping and wailing for the finall deſtruction of the great ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall City of Babilon, <hi>ſaying Alas, Alas, for in one hower ſhe is made deſolate &amp; naked. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>er.</hi> 15.16.17.18. <hi>For ſhe doth been drunke with the Blood of the Saints and of the Martyrs of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt which ſhe hath ſpilt in great aboundance, like water upon the ground, but the day is almoſt come, wherein the Juſtice of God will render her a full recompence with Vengence and Fury: <hi>Wherefore to you all</hi> Gods people <hi>that yet is in her, Come out of her &amp; depart from her,</hi> for if you ſtay in her you will partake of her <hi>ſinnes,</hi> in dſobeying Gods commands and ſo will be lyable and open to his <hi>Plagues, wrath and Fury: for her ſinnes have reached unto the Heavens, &amp; God hath remembred her Iniquities.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let us call together the <hi>Archers &amp; valiant Spear-men of the Lord,</hi> and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:154971:24"/>
to our duty <hi>Let us ſet our ſelves in Array againſt her, &amp; campe rownd about her, &amp; ſhoot at her, without mercy: and let none that belong unto her eſcape your</hi> ſpirituall Darts, <hi>but let us reward her even as ſhe hath rewarded us, &amp; dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble unto her double according to her workes, in the Cup which ſhee hath filled to us, let us fill to her d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uble: for ſhe hath beene exceeding proud againſt the</hi> Lord <hi>of</hi> Hoaſts, <hi>even againſt the</hi> Holy One <hi>of</hi> Iſrael. <hi>Jer.</hi> 50.8.14.29. <hi>&amp;</hi> 51.6.9.10. <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.4.5.6.</p>
            <p>And alſo, I will maintaine that the Church of <hi>Rome as it is called,,</hi> and as at this day it ſtands, and hath done for above a Thouſand years, neither is nor never was, a true viſible Church of Chriſt. It is true, there was a true Church in <hi>Rome</hi> and at <hi>Rome,</hi> but never of <hi>Rome:</hi> the members of which were <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Beleevers,</hi> but the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> now conſiſts of all ſorts and kinds of wicked and ungodly perſons, which they force by <hi>ſpirituall Tyranny</hi> if they refuſe to ſubmit unto them. <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.15.16. Yea the common <hi>Strum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets &amp; Whores,</hi> that pay ſo many thowſands in the year to the <hi>Popes</hi> Graceleſſe Impiety for keeping publique and open <hi>Stew-houſes</hi> even in <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelfe, for all eommers and goers: are as good members of the Church thereof and as well accepted of as the beſt they have. And thus I have punctually anſwered the ſecond thing that you deſire your friend to take notice of, which is, that <hi>Corruptions may be in a true Church,</hi> which I have granted, but yet have proued that it is their ſinne: &amp; the continuance in their corruptions, will overthrow their Eſſence &amp; being, &amp; make Chriſt to begon from them and ſo unchurch them.</p>
            <p>Alſo I have ſhewed that it ſerves nothing to the benefit of your Church, ſeing you are not able to prove that ever it was true.</p>
            <p>Now to that which I have ſaid, and by the Authority of the ſacred word of God proved, I chalenge your particular and punctuall Anſwer in writing wiſhing you to goe to W. B. and G. W. who hoth have been main ſticklers &amp; enemies of late to the truth of God, profeſſed by the totall Seperation; and deſire their beſt and ableſt aſiſtance, for I beleeve that ſome of your nine flexible Erronious &amp; Antichriſtian Argumenss were digged out of their Leaden Mines, wherefore with importunity, without any deniall, deſire them to helpe you to reply in writing, to this my publique anſwer, otherwiſe I will ſay and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime it, that you all three are fearefull cowards, and but the ignorant, darke, night, bragging and ſcreeching Owles of Antichriſt. Now out of that you have largely proved you ſay (but I affirme) you have proved nothing at all to the purpoſe, you infer thoſe four Concluſions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That all the Deſcriptions &amp; Definitions of a viſible</hi> Church, <hi>given by the</hi> Separation <hi>are all falſe, becauſe they will have none but</hi> Saints <hi>in their</hi> Church, <hi>to be the matter of it.</hi> 2. <hi>That all their buildings are falſe.</hi> 3. <hi>That the ground of their</hi> Separation <hi>is not ſound, ſeing that in a true viſible</hi> Church <hi>there have
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:154971:24"/>
beene knowne wicked men.</hi> 4. <hi>From hence you infer, that it is lawfull and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable to have ſpirituall Communion mith known wicked men in a religious wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip ſeing they are the greateſt part of a viſible Ch. &amp; then to conclude all, you ſay many more things you might have ſet downe if time had permitted, but theſe you ſay are ſufficient.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, that theſe four Concluſions are all of them wicked, Antichriſtian and damnable: without all warrant in the leaſt from the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as as I have already largly proved; therefore they are not in the leaſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to ſatisfie the Conſeicnce of any man or woman: I trvly deſire to walk-in Gods ways, therefore if you would ſtill keepe your Freind a ſubjected ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to Antichriſt, as you your ſelfe are, then publiquely in writing aun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſwer that which here I have writ, otherwiſe I beleeve and hope that you will looſe her with many moe beſides ere long, ſo leving you unto Baall for whom you plead and ſtand vp ſalyng with the ſpirit of God in <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.11. <hi>he that is unjuſt let him be unjuſt ſtill, and he that is filthy let him be filthy ſtill, and he that is righteous let him be righteous ſtill, he that is holy let him be holy ſtill;</hi> yet for all that if you belong to Gods Election of Grace, I deſire for you, as it is my duty, that God would reveale his truthe, counſels and ſecrets unto you, which he doth leſſe or more to all thoſe that truly feore him, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 25.12.14. <hi>Pro.</hi> 3.32. <hi>Mar.</hi> 4.34. and that you may give true declaration of your unfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned repentance for your great ſin, for ſtanding for Antichriſts Kingdome, with all your might, and for ſo bitter and malitious oppoſing and reviling the truth of God, and the true profeſſours thereof, which if God give you not grace to doe, aſſuredly know, that ſeeing you have fallen upon the cheife corner ſtone Jeſus Chriſt, he will deſtroy and breake you, but if he fall upon, as you may juſtly feare, he will grind you all to duſt and powder, <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.44. Therefore as you love your ſoule, looke to it, ſeeing you are now admoniſhed by me your Oppoſite. And ſo</p>
            <p>I reſt your oppoſing Oppugner in the truthes behalfe againſt all Antichriſt are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ours and maintainers thereof, though in moſt cruell and cloſe impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in Irons with my bloody Prelaticall enemies deſire and hope will ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly put a period to my dayes.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Lilburne.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <date>Anno. <hi>1638.</hi>
                  </date> which to me is the ſecond yeare of Remembrance, and the <hi>21</hi> yeere of my age.</dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <p>From the <hi>Fleet</hi> the Prelats fiery Furnace, yet to me God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat made it a delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and rejoycing Pallace and Caſtle, in which I ſtand <hi>Sentinell</hi> night and day, to defend Sion the City of the living God from her enemies, and to oppoſe all her op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers, deſiring all my fellow brethren, that profeſſe the ſame truth with me, as va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant and worthy Soldiers of Jeſus Chriſt to lend me their beſt and corragious aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, with the choyſeſt of their ſpirituall weapons, that ſowe may haue in hand with violence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ble downe in the ground the tottering confuſed Tower of <hi>Babel</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:154971:25"/>
Theſe Verſes were my meditations one night in my cloſe Impriſnment after the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of a <hi>pamphlet</hi> ſung in the ſtreets of <hi>London,</hi> in which I was joyned as a <hi>Traytour</hi> with the <hi>Scots</hi> at their firſt comeing into England.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>The Lord our God is both firme and ſtable,</l>
               <l>And all his Councels and Decrees unalterable:</l>
               <l>Which when they ſurly ſhall accompliſh'd be,</l>
               <l>The downfall of his enemies we ſhall ſee:</l>
               <l>Which I by faith doe apprehend to be at hand,</l>
               <l>Which fils my ſoule with zeale full faſt to ſtand,</l>
               <l>To that renowned cauſe, for which in bonds I lye.</l>
               <l>Seeing his prayſe and truth doth ſpread thereby.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O happy be the day, that he me brought</l>
               <l>Unto my ſorrowes, for they unto my thought</l>
               <l>doe ſerve to be the choyſeſt ſafety can be found</l>
               <l>Upon this vaine and empty earthly ground:</l>
               <l>For in them my ſoule ſuch large experience hath got</l>
               <l>Of that celeſtiall treſure, that ne're ſhall rot,</l>
               <l>But will for <hi>ay</hi> and <hi>ay</hi> endure,</l>
               <l>As long as God's both ſtable, firme and ſure:</l>
               <l>The like whereof I apprehend can not be had</l>
               <l>As liberty, though my eſtate eſteem'd be had.</l>
               <l>Therefore for ever prayſed be my God,</l>
               <l>That no my houſe of clay hath laid his rod</l>
               <l>In loving kindnes, mercy, and in favour,</l>
               <l>That ſo my ſoule from him might never waver.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wherefore before I will his Truth deny,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Reſolv,d</hi> I <hi>am at</hi> Stake to dye.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Lilburne.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>p.</hi> 2. <hi>l.r. Deut.</hi> 16.16. <hi>p.l.</hi> 12. <hi>r</hi> to you my <hi>l.</hi> 18. that her. <hi>l.</hi> 16. <hi>r.</hi> ſo knit. <hi>l.</hi> 29. <hi>r.</hi> ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of. <hi>p</hi> 6. <hi>l</hi> 11. <hi>r.</hi> beſt. <hi>p.</hi> 9. <hi>l.</hi> 41. <hi>r.</hi> one of. <hi>p.</hi> 10. <hi>l.</hi> 16. <hi>dele</hi> 54. 7. <hi>l.</hi> 91. <hi>r.</hi> yet for all. <hi>p.</hi> 12. <hi>r.</hi> of faith <hi>l.</hi> 29. and unleſſe. <hi>l</hi> 31. <hi>dele</hi> without a lawfull authority given and received from him. <hi>p</hi> 14. <hi>l.</hi> 13 they are. <hi>p.</hi> 19. <hi>l</hi> 3. <hi>r.</hi> to obſerve. <hi>l.</hi> 19. <hi>r.</hi> I challenge. <hi>l.</hi> 20. <hi>r.</hi> your people. <hi>p.</hi> 20. <hi>l.</hi> 28. <hi>r.</hi> bind. <hi>p.</hi> 21. <hi>l.</hi> 21. <hi>r.</hi> feeding <hi>p.</hi> 25. <hi>l.r.</hi> therefore. <hi>p.</hi> 26. <hi>l.</hi> 28. <hi>r. Gal.</hi> 5. <hi>p.</hi> 30. <hi>l.</hi> 25. <hi>r.</hi> failings <hi>p.</hi> 31. <hi>r. only. p.</hi> 36. <hi>r. vnder l. r.</hi> of <hi>l. in Syon. p.</hi> 39. <hi>l.r.</hi> never can be. <hi>p.</hi> 40. <hi>l.</hi> 13. <hi>dele</hi> though.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
